好的，那我们开始吧。
Okay, yeah, let's get started.
首先，关于后勤安排，请尽快完成交叉阀门，好吗？
So so logistics update, please finish the cross valve, okay?
完成80%你就能得到两分。
80% and you'll get two points.
下周二我们有考试，我已经让助教安排答疑课，
Next Tuesday, we'll have exam, and I have asked TA to hold recitation,
可能是这周五或下周一，确保你们能通过考试，好吗？
probably this Friday or next Monday, to make sure you pass exam, okay?
如果你不能来，我们当然会有录播，
And we will have a recording, of course, if you're not able to attend,
你只需要看录播就行了。
just, you know, watch the recording.
好的，那我们回到主要内容。
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, let's back to the main content.
今天我们要讲一些非常非常及时的内容。
So today, we are going to talk about some really, really, I would say timely content.
也就是模型推理和服务。
So m serving an inference.
好吗？我觉得这基本上就是现在硅谷正在努力做的事情，
Okay? I think this is basically what the current Silicon Valley is grinding,
比如开放 Google Demand，所有这些基础设施公司。
like open Google Demand, all these infrastructure companies.
他们基本上都在实现 M 推理。
They are basically opplementing M inference.
是的，为了获得完美的利润率，嗯，来为 Ms 提供服务。
Yeah, in order to make a perfect margin, um, for serving Ms.
好吗？我们回到刚才的话题。
Okay? Let's go back.
简单回顾一下，好吗？
Just a little bit recap, okay?
所以这是我们的 RM，对吧？
So this is our RM, right?
我们基本上得到了一个 ex token 预测器。
So we basically get a ex token predictor.
我觉得你明白这个意思，对吧？
I think you understand this, okay?
这就是我们的 M 推理过程，对吧？
And this is our M inference process, right?
基本上，我们有一个prom，也就是一串token序列。
So basically, we have a prom, which is a sequence of tokens.
然后我们把这个token输入到
And we give this token to
RM中，经过所有层的前向传播，我们预测下一个token。
RM and we perform forward pass through all the layers, and we predict next token.
这是第一步，叫做prefile或者prompt组合。
That is the first step, which is called prefile or prompt combination.
好的，然后在第一步之后，
Okay. And then after the first step,
我们基本上开始生成新的token，然后把新token再输入到神经网络中，
We basically start, um, generating new token and, um, we give the new token back to the neurotw arm,
并尝试生成下一个token。
and we try to generate next token.
我们会重复这个过程，直到达到arm的最大序列长度，或者
We repeat until we hit in, say, the maximum sequence length of the arm or when
生成了序列结束的token，对吧？
we generate end of sequence token, US, right?
这就是推理过程。
This is the inference process, okay?
简单总结一下，我们可以从计算的角度来看，
To summarize a little bit, we can from a computational perspective,
嗯，我的推理基本上分为两个阶段。
um, my inference is essentially two phases.
第一个阶段我们称之为预填充。
The first phase we call prefill.
也就是你在计算提示词。
That is you are computing the prompt.
第二个阶段叫做解码。
The second phase is called decoding.
很明显，预填充对应于第零次迭代，
And apparently prefill corresponds to the zeros iteration that is
也就是你处理提示词并尝试立即生成提示词后的下一个标记。
you process a prompt and try to generate it immediately the next token, after the prompt.
然后这个预填充只进行一次，
And then this prefill is only conducted once,
对吧，因为你只需要处理一次预填充，
right because you just need to process your prefill once,
然后你就开始重复你的解码过程，
and then you start repeating your decoding,
每次你只能解码一个标记。
Every time you only decode one token.
为什么？因为这是自回归解码，我已经重复过了。
Why? Because it's autoregressive decoding, I already repeat that.
在你知道当前标记之前，你无法预测未来的标记，明白吗？
You cannot predict future tokens before you know the current token, okay?
嗯，记住这一点，好吗，预字段解码。
Um, remember this, okay, pre field decoding.
这是推理的计算特性。
That is the computational characteristics of inference.
好的。还有一个关于M推理的组成部分是，我们实际上还维护了另一个，我可以说，
Okay. And one more component for M inference is, we actually maintain another, I would say,
数据或数据结构，这叫做键值缓存。
data or data structure, which is called key value cache.
在这里，键值基本上对应于注意力机制中的键和值。
So here, key value basically corresponds to the QQVuh in attention the key and the values.
好的，所以从高层来看，这个键值缓存基本上帮助我们节省了一些计算。
Okay. So high level, at a high level, this key value cache basically help us save some competion.
但让我们看看什么是键值缓存。
But let's look at what is key value cache.
好的。那么在左边，
Okay. So on the left hand side,
我认为这基本上就是你们非常熟悉的对话图。
I think it's basically the conversational graph that you guys have been very familiar with.
而在右边，基本上是一个图表，
And on the right hand side is basically a chief,
我从某处引用的，它展示了推理过程，好吗？
I quoted from somewhere, which shows the inference process, okay?
当你计算左边的部分，嗯，就是在注意力机制时，对吧？
When you compute that left part of, um, at tensing, right?
所以如果你看这个，当我们进行推理时，
So if you look at this, so when we do our inference,
我们每次做的事情就是观察在上一步生成的新token。
what do we do is every time we observe a new token, generated in the previous step.
然后我们把这个新token和之前已经
And then we concatenate this new token with the previous already
生成的token以及前缀拼接起来，然后输入到神经网络中，
generated token and the prefel and we forward that into the neural network
以便计算下一个token。
in order to compute the next togen.
When we compute the next token, we only care about the query of the next togen, right?
And we like this query of next token to attend to all the key values of previous tokens, right?
So if you look at this computation, this chief is basically trying to illustrate
the process I just described, okay?
So why there is a key value catch is because basically we compute
this when we continue this decoding process, if we are able to save the previous tokens,
Q and V, we can avoid a lot of computation, okay?
And to illustrate this, you basically can look at these two differs, okay?
On the upper hand side, um, you basically see a computation
where the key value caches are not catched.
Key values are not catched, okay?
And on the bottom part, you are seeing a computation where the keys
and values of previous steps are catched.
And you can clear the difference, right?
So basically, every time, if we don't save the key keys and values in attention of previous tokens.
So every time we decode the new token, we need to this query we need to recompute
the previous KV and then this new token query to attend to all the KVs, right?
But if you are able to catch this KV of previous generating steps, then we just need to perform one,
uh attention competition, and we already know the previous KVs.
We just like this query to attend to all the keys and values to generate, you know, the results.
好吗？这部分有任何问题吗？
Okay? Any questions on this part?
好的。本质上，KV缓存是一种计算优化方式，
Okay. Essentially, KV catch is a kind of a computation optation where
我们用一些额外的内存来保存中间结果，对吧？这样可以加速解码过程，对吗？
we treat some additional memory to save for commutation, right to accelerate the decoding, okay?
那么我有两个问题，想确保你真的理解了这个过程。
Then I have two questions, okay, to make sure you really understand this process.
好吗？第一个问题是，在预填充阶段，KV缓存会发生什么？
Okay? The first one is what happens on KV catch in prefilled phase?
那为什么在预填充阶段会有所谓的QV缓存呢？
So why in prefilled there's like a so called QV catch?
这是因为在预填充阶段我们能看到所有的token。
It's because in pref we see all the tokens.
我们只需要对所有token做一次前向计算，
We just perform one forward across all the tokens and
每个token位置都会生成对应的KV缓存。
all the KV catches are generated for each token position.
所以我们不需要缓存之前的token，然后等待下一个token生成。
So we don't how to basically catch the previous tokens and wait for the next token to generate.
好吗？在性能阶段的KV缓存中，我们正在一次性生成所有已观察到的token的QV缓存。
Okay? What happens on KV catch in perfs phase, we are generating a QV cache of
只需一遍就能把所有token都缓存下来。
all observed tokens in one pass.
我们需要缓存Q查询吗？
Do we need to catch Q query?
因为在注意力机制中，我们有
Because in attention, we have
QQV，我们需要缓存查询吗？
QQV do we need to catch query?
不，我们不知道查询，因为我们必须看到那个token才能知道查询内容。
No, we don't know the query because we have to see that token in order to know the query.
当我们计算下一个token的结果时，我们用当前token的查询去
And when we compute the results of the next token, we are using the current tokens query to
关注所有之前token的QV。
attend to all previous token QVs.
如果我们没看到那个token，就不知道查询是什么。
Don't know if we don't see that token, we don't know the query.
所以我们不能缓存Q，明白了吗？
Therefore, we cannot catch Q. Okay?
好的。现在你理解了QV捕获，我们再来做一次。
Okay. Now you understand QV catch and then let's do this again,
我认为我们之前是为了训练做的，现在我们再为推理做一次。
I think we do this for training and now, let's do this for uh inference again.
所以，我们还要关注计算机内存和通信。
So, we also want to look at computer memory and communication.
那么在推理中会发生什么，以及可能出现的瓶颈是什么。
So what happens in inference and what could be the potential for the neck.
好吗？如果我们看计算，就像我说的，对于推理来说，计算机基本上是
Okay? If we look at compute, okay, like I said, for inference, the computer essentially um is
由两个阶段组成的，预填充和解码。
consisted of two phases, prefill and decoding.
我们一个一个来看。对于预填充来说，基本上和训练是一样的。
So we look at one by one. So for prefills essentially the same training.
没有变化，对吧？你观察整个序列，
Nothing changes, right? You observe the entire sequence,
你只是把这个序列输入到语言模型中，对吧？
you just forward that sequence into language model, okay?
所以没有区别。那么对于解码，你会注意到一件事
So no difference. So for decoding, one thing you noted that is
因为每次我们只生成一个标记，我们无法生成未来的标记，对吧。
because every time we only generate the one token, we are not able to generate future tokens, right.
所以在解码时，当我们将这个标记输入到神经网络中时，
So therefore, in decoding, when we forward this token into through the neural network,
我们必须将S设置为1，对吗？
we have to set S equal to one, right?
也就是生成一个标记，我们只计算一个标记。
That is generating one token, we're computing one token.
明白了吗？我觉得如果你看这个图表，
Okay? I think if you look at this graph,
我希望能一再强调这一点。
I hoping emphasize this again and again.
那么S等于1的问题是什么？
So what is the problem of S equal to one?
它会影响我们的算术强度，因为最大尺寸
It will hurt our arithmetic intensity, because the maximal sizes are
被缩减成一维，也就是1，明白吗？
being reduced into one dimension is one, okay?
神经网络的内存方面，有一点新的是在训练时，我们基本上把所有序列都放进网络
The net spoken memory, one thing new is in training, we all basically put all the sequence network
或者我们可以一次性计算出QBatch，然后我们丢弃梯度并更新参数，
or compute the QBach in one pass, and then we drup gradients and we updated parameters,
然后我们把所有东西都丢掉，对吧？
and we throw everything away, right?
但在推理时，我们不能把这个QB缓存丢掉。
But in inference, we cannot throw this QB cache away.
为什么？因为我们要不断地生成一个token、一个token、一个token，好吗？
Why? Because we continue to generate one token, one token, one token, okay?
而且每次我们只能生成一个token，不能多于一个。
And every time we can only generate one token, but not more than one.
所以我们必须在这个请求的整个生命周期内保留这个QB缓存，
So we have to persist this QB cache, right through the lifetime of this request,
直到这个序列的所有token都被生成并完成。
this sequence until all the tokens have been generated and excited.
这意味着我们必须长时间保存这个缓存。
That means that we have to always save this vocacy for considerably long period of time.
这会给我们的内存带来一些压力，稍后我会详细讲。
This will give us a little bit memory pressure, which I will talk about later.
那通信方面呢？
What about the communication?
实际上，通信方面没有任何变化。
In fact, there's nothing changed for communication.
基本上是一样的，因为偏好和解码通信是一样的。
It's almost the same because prefer and decoding communication is the same.
无论你选择哪种并行方式，你基本上都会继承
Whatever kind palism you want to choose, you will basically inherit from
我们在训练中讨论过的那些技术。
the same techniques we talked about in training.
事实上，在推理阶段，并行性甚至更简单，为什么呢？
In fact, inference, the paralysm is even simpler, why?
因为我们没有梯度。
Because we don't have a gradient.
我们基本上没有反向传播计算图。
We don't have um, basically, we don't have that back chord graph.
我们没有最优状态。
We don't have optimal states.
记住，在训练中，最优状态是你消耗最多内存的地方，16。
Remember in arm training, optimal states is where you consume the most memory, 16.
记住这个因素。而在这里，我们没有这个问题。
Remember that factor. And here we don't have that.
这意味着我们在保存中间状态、保存参数时的内存压力要小得多。
That means that our memory pressure on saving the intermediate states on saving the parameters on
保存最优状态时的压力也要低很多。
saving the optimal states are much lower.
主要是哈希缓存，对吧？
It's mainly caving hash, okay?
好的，我觉得我们基本上看完了这些，已经涵盖了计算机内存和通信部分。
Okay, I think we basically look at this, we go through computer memory and communication.
我还有一个问题。那么比特大小B怎么办？
I have additional question. So how about bit size B?
那么这和推理有什么不同？
So what makes this different inference?
好的，我们来谈谈这个问题，好吗？
Okay, let's talk about that, okay?
在训练时，你总是固定一个静态的比特集，对吧？
So in training, you always fixed a static bisets right?
因为你有一个数据集，你只需要获取一个静态的比特集。
So because you have a dataset, you just fetch a static body sets.
但在推理时，这就不一样了。
But in inference, it's different.
你的批量大小取决于你收到多少流量。
Your boy size is determined by how many traffic you receive.
就像我在控制终端点一样。
Like I'm holding arm end point.
我不知道我的用户什么时候会提交请求。
I don't know when my users will submit my request.
就像我什么时候会提交一个谷歌查询一样，
It's like when I will submit a google query,
我必须非常聪明地决定如何设置电池容量。
I have to make a very smart decision how I make the battery size.
我应该发送一批
Should I send a batch of
1000个到终端点，以最大化我的原始强度，
1,000 to the endpoint to maximize my original intensity,
还是我一收到一个请求，
or should I just once I receive one request,
就立刻把它发送到终端点。
I immediately send it to endpoint.
这两种方式有区别吗？因为如果我等着累积到1000的批量大小，
This two has difference? Because if I wait to accumulate a batch size of 1,000,
then the first user will be mad with me because he's waiting for other users to submit queries.
But if I receive one request,
I immediately submit, what's the problem? My bist is equal to one.
Then my TPU is under utilized.
Okay? So you are facing a very like a customer phasing question.
That is how you exactly make this batch, okay?
Which means that in inference, the speed is variable.
Okay? You have to correlate the speed with your traffic with a lot of computation
or utilization kind of thing, okay?
So that's why inference, basically the techniques are developed around this B.
好的。我们基本上考虑两种情况。
Okay. And we essentially consider two scenarios.
第一种情况是我们有一个很大的B。
The first scenario is that we have a large B.
第二种情况是我们有一个很小的B。
The second scenario, we have a small B.
我还要让这个对比更加极端，好吗？
And I'm going to make this even more extreme, okay?
所以当我们有一个很大的B时，我们基本上就像谷歌和OpenAI一样。
So we have a large B, we are basically Google and open a.
我们在服务一个arm，每天都会收到数百万的请求，对吧？
We are serving arm where every day we observe millions of requests, okay?
我们把这种情况称为arm服务。
And we call this arm serving, okay?
另一种情况下，我们有一个很小的B，比如B等于1。
And in another case, basically, we have a small B, for example, B equal to one.
也就是说，你在你的笔记本电脑上部署了arm，你将是唯一的用户，对吗？
That is, develop you deploy your arm on your laptop and you will be the only user, right?
你想要针对这种小规模进行优化。
And you want to optimize for this small
B. 我想在上周四，你们已经听说过这种用于优化小B的数据技术了。
B. I think in last Thursday, you have already heard this data technique for optimizing small B.
它基本上就是推测解码。
It's basically speculative decoding.
你不用关心比特集，只是想加速
You don't care about the bit sets, and you just want to accelerate
单个请求的推理延迟。
the inference latency of a single request.
因此，我们一直在开发很多推测编码技术，
Therefore, we have been developing a lot of speculative coding techniques,
比如 equal one、two、three。
for example, equal one, two, three.
但今天，我会把你们的注意力转移到第一个，也就是如何优化RTB。
But today, I will shift your focus to the first one, how will optimize RTB.
在这里，你们可能已经感觉到为什么Open和Google会投入大量资源在这上面。
And here, you probably already sense why Open and Google, they put a lot of resources on this.
因为如果你能把这个做得更好，基本上你可以用更少的GPU来服务更多的请求。
Because if you can do this better, you can basically you can use less GPUs to serve more requests.
如果你能用更少的GPU解决更多的请求，
And if you're able to solve more requests using less GPUs,
你可以获得更高的利润率，因为你会根据用户消耗的每个 token 收费。
you are creating a higher profit margin because you charge your der for each token they consumed.
基本上，如果你能降低成本，剩下的部分就很完美了。你可以从中赚钱。
Basically, if you can reduce your cost, then the rest is perfect. You can make money from that.
明白吗？这就是为什么很多公司会投入大量资金，确保他们能解决
Okay? That's why a lot of sitting companies they are investing a lot to make sure they can solve
尽可能多的请求，同时使用最少的 GPU。
the most request using the fewest GPUs.
好的，明白了。
Okay, cool.
那么，在这个大模型 B 的场景下，
Then, in this large B scenario,
我想我已经强调过，主要的衡量指标是我们称之为“每次查询成本”的指标。
I think I already emphasized the main metric is one metric we called cost per query.
也就是你解决一个查询需要花多少钱。
That is how much you can solve a query, how much you need to pay.
如果我们把这个“每次查询成本”翻译一下，其实就是一个商业术语，对吧？
And if we translate this cross query is basically a business term, right?
但如果我们把这个商业术语再转化为一些更具体的东西的话
But if we translate this business term into something that is
更准确地说，一个系统基本上就是吞吐量。
more like a system is basically throughput.
比如说，你每秒能处理多少个token，比如用八块GPU或六块GPU。
For example, how many tokens you can solve per second, using say, eight GPs or six GPUs.
好吗？接下来，我们要讲几个非常关键的技术，
Okay? Next, we are going to talk about a few very key techniques that we
可以最大化这个吞吐量，好吗？
can maximize this throughput, okay?
但在那之前，我想更深入地探讨一下大B推理时遇到的问题。
But before that, I want to dive deeper into the problems of inference at a large B.
也就是一个很大的B size。
So basically a large B size.
有几个问题我想指出来，我希望你们真的能理解这一点。
So, there are a few problems that I want to point out and I want you to indeed understand this.
我们还是会这样做，主要是计算机内存和通信。
Again, I think we are going to do this, computer memory and communication.
至于通信，这不是问题，因为它和训练时是一样的。
And for communication, not a problem, because, uh it's the same with the training.
没有什么变化，甚至更简单，因为没有开放状态。
Nothing changes and it's easier, even easier because there is no open state.
那我们就专注于计算和内存，好吗。
So we'll focus on compute and memory, okay.
关于计算，我刚才说了，在推理阶段，有预取和解码两个部分。
So for computer, I said, I'm inference, there's prefew and decode.
那我们就一个一个来看。
So let's look at one by one.
那预取阶段有什么问题呢？
So for prefew what's the problem.
现在你有一个很大的字节大小，这一批请求是由用户提交的，
So now you have a large bite size, and this batch of requests are submitted by users,
而你的用户基本上每个人输入的提示词都不一样。
and your user basically type a different prompt to the point.
你无法控制我们输入了什么提示词。
And you have no control of what prompts the we type.
那第一个问题是什么呢？
So what's the first problem?
如果你还记得我这门课的第一节课，我说过，你们面临的问题是
If you remember my first lecture in this course, I said, you are facing a problem where
每个请求的 token 数量都不一样，对吧？
each request has a different number of tokens. Right?
因为我可以问一个更简短的问题，而你可以问一个更长的问题。
Because I can ask a shorter question and you can ask a longer question.
然后你们都把这些问题交给我，让我想办法怎么让电池比赛变得更好。
And you all give these questions to my arm on how I can make the battery competition.
好吗？我记得在我的第一堂课上，我说过，有一种解决方法其实就是，
Okay? I think in my first lecture, I said, one way to address that is basically,
不管问题多短还是多长，你基本上把最短的补齐到最长的长度。
no matter how short or how long, you basically pad the shortest to longest.
这其实非常愚蠢。
And this is super stupid.
就像我说的，如果你这么做，你在提供服务时是赚不到钱的。
Like I said, if you do this, you are going to not make any money from serving irons.
好，第一个问题是，不同的提示长度差异很大。
Okay? So the first problem is different prompts have very different lens.
那你到底应该怎么补齐它们呢？
So how you exactly should patch them?
绝对不是用补齐的办法。
Okay, definitely not padding.
补齐其实是在浪费TPR，明白吗？
Padding is wasting TPRs, ok?
第二个问题是无法解码，解码是个问题。
The second problem is undecodeUndecod was a problem.
我可以问你非常难的问题，也可以让另一个人问很简单的问题，
I can ask you very difficult query and another person as simple query,
比如“一加一等于几”，对吧？
like what is one plus one, right?
而答案只需要一个词。
And the answer is a single token.
但我也可以让你做一些深度研究，
But I can let you do some kind of deep research,
基本上就是告诉我整个领域的最新进展。
basically tell me what's going on in this entire field.
所以问题在于，不同的用户可以提交不同的问题，你事先并不知道
So the problem is different user can submit different queries and you don't know ahead of time
每个问题你会生成多少词。
that how many tokens you will generate for each query.
可能会非常长，也可能会非常短，对吧？你永远无法预知。
It could be super long or it could be super short, right? And you never know.
即使作为开放者，我也不知道，因为这取决于RM。
Even as open, I don't know because this is up to the RM.
如果RM到达美国，基本上就会被终止。
And if the RM reach US, it will basically be terminated.
所以第二个问题是在阶段中的理想状态。这是非常动态的。
So the second problem is ideal in phase. This is super dynamic.
明白吗？你不知道不同的提示会生成不同数量的未知token。
Okay? You don't know different prompts have different unknown number generated tokens.
明白吗？但你仍然希望从服务提供者的角度来看，
Okay? But you still want to make sure from a service provider's perspective,
你想确保最大限度地利用你的GPU来处理各种请求，对吧？
you want to make sure you maximally utilize your GPUs to service kind of requests, okay?
就像我说的，解码还有另一个问题，我再强调一下。
And like I said, another problem with decoding I reiterate, okay.
所以基本上每个请求进入解码阶段时，
So basically for each request, when they enter decoding phase,
他们的序列长度等于一。
they have a sequence that equal to one.
那问题是什么呢？
And what's the problem?
如果你无法组成一个非常大的批次，对吧？
So if you are not able to make a super big batch, right?
对于所有这些序列等于一次解码请求的情况，你的GPO肯定没有被充分利用，
For all these sequence equal to one decoding requests, your GPO is definitely under utilized,
因为GPO在标量推荐方面并不是特别擅长。
because GPO is not super good at scalar recommendation.
它在其他方面还不错，比如说在某些任务上，对吧？
It's pretty good at, uh like met more, right?
所以基本上在解码阶段，你必须做一个非常大的批处理。
Okay? So basically decoding phase, you have to make a super big batch.
但是怎么做到这一点呢？这是个问题。
But how to make that? That's a problem.
好的，而且在内存方面，我们还有另一个问题，对吧。
Okay. And also on memory, we have another problem, right.
因为B很大，这意味着你会有很多很多的请求。
So because B is large, right, that means that you are going to have many many requests.
每个请求都会生成、生成、再生成。
Ich request is going to generate generator generate.
所以基本上，纵向上，你有很大的位宽，
So basically, vertically, you have a large bit size,
这对应着很多请求，而横向上，
which corresponds to many requests, and horizontally,
你有请求在持续生成tokens，并且你不会释放
you have Is requests continue to generate tokens, and you are not going to release
某个请求的KV缓存，直到该请求完成。
a QB cache for I request until that request finishes.
这意味着如果你持续增加你的batch size，并且继续
That means that if you continue to increase your Bdysize and you continue
生成更多的tokens，你就必须线性地增加分配给KV缓存的内存。
to generate one more tokens, you have to linearly increase the memory you allocate to see QB caches.
在某个时刻，这些KV缓存会占据你大部分的内存，最终会导致你的GPU崩溃。
And at some point, that QV case will dominate your memory usage, and it will explode your GPU.
那么你如何管理这个问题呢？这就涉及到KV缓存了，好吗？
So how you manage this is going to KV cash, okay?
基本上，为了解决这些问题，接下来我们要讨论两个非常基础
Um, so basically to address these problems, we Next are going to talk about the two very fundamental
并且非常及时的技术。
and very, very, timely techniques.
其中一个叫做连续补丁（continuous patching）。
One is called continuous patching.
这是一个关键技术，大约在一年前，也许是两年前，也就是2023年被发明出来的。
That is a key technique that invented one year ago, maybe two years ago, 2023.
嗯，这项技术基本上提升了吞吐量。
Um that technique basically improves the throughput.
也就是说，你可以生成的token数量提升了20倍。
That is the number of tokens you can generate by 20 X.
明白吗？这是一个关键性的突破。
Okay? That is a key breakthrough.
第二项技术主要是解决内存问题。
And the second technique is basically addressing the memory problem.
也就是你如何高效地管理KB缓存。
That is how you can efficiently manage KB cache.
这项技术被称为页面注意力（page attention），
And that technique is called page attention,
页面注意力基本上也提升了吞吐量。
and that page attention basically improve the throughput.
也就是说，你可以服务的token数量增加了。
That is the number token you can serve.
但又提升了三倍。基本上，
But another three times. Basically, what
我想说的是，在过去一年半里，所有人都在运行
I'm trying to say is in the past 1.5 a year, all the people are running
这样他们基本上能够，至少提供
this and they are able to basically, improve at least provide
比两年前提升了60倍的改进。
improvement of 60 times compared to two years ago.
好的。这意味着推理正在变得有点商品化，
Okay. So that means m inference is being kind of commoditized,
嗯，但在我讲解技术之前，
o. Um, but before I move into techniques,
我还想再重申一下，以帮助你更好地理解，比如说等于一的情况。
I want to also, reiterate a little bit to enhance your understanding of um, would be equal to one.
好的？那么等于一，会有什么问题呢？
Okay? So equal to one, what's the problem.
那么为什么推测性编码有效呢？
So why is speculative coding works?
我认为到目前为止，你已经理解了推测性编码的基本原理。
I think by far, you already understood the basic rationale behind speculative.
但让我们从系统的角度来看，而不是从算法的角度。
But let's look at it from a system perspective, but not from algorithm perspective.
那么对于B等于一，会有什么问题呢？
So for B B equal to one. What's the problem?
所以前馈阶段，就像我说的，没有问题，对吧，
So for pre field, like I said, there's no problem, right,
因为它基本上是一个单一序列，你像训练一样进行计算。
because it's basically a single sequence and you proceed the computation
没问题。
as if you are doing training. Okay, no problem.
但是在解码时，也会面临同样的问题，就是你不知道
But for decode, it also face the same problem that is you don't know
你会生成多少个token，对吧？
how many token you are going to generate, right?
但这没关系。这总比B等于一个很大的B要好。
But that's okay. It's better than B equal to great B is a large number.
另一个B等于1的问题在于，这里你有B等于1，S也等于1。
Okay? Another problem for Bequal to one is here, you have B equal to one, you have S equal to one.
好的，现在你看到问题了。
Okay. And now you see the problem.
如果你基本上移动你的呃，如果你把你的眼睛放在这里，记住，这里只有三个维度。
If you basically shift your uh if you put your eye here, remember, these are only three dimensions.
现在，你有两个维度都等于1。
Now, you have two dimension which are equal to one.
你只有一个维度基本上不等于一。
You only have one dimension that is basically not equal to one.
这意味着无论你在这里启动什么内核，都不会特别高效，
This means that whatever kernels you launch here, it's not going to be super efficient,
因为它无法利用所有的GPU。
because it's not able to uti all the GPUs.
明白了吗？那么问题是什么？
Okay? So what's that problem?
明白了吗？我稍后会再讲解。
Okay? I will review later.
但在我结束之前，关于内存我没有问题，因为
But before I finish, um for memory I don't have a problem because
我只需要解决一个请求。
I only need to solve one request.
所以很难让一个请求占满P的内存，除非
So it's very hard for one request to set by P memory unless
你真的为那个请求生成了很多tokens。
you generally want me tokens for that request.
好的，那我们回到这个问题。
Okay. Then let's go back to this one.
问题是S等于1，B等于1。
What's the problem as equal to one, B equal to one.
如果你还记得，我们想要最大化这个。
If you remember this, we want to maximize this.
但在这里你有S等于1，B等于1。
But here you have equals one, B equal to one.
记住，当S等于1时，
Remember, when S equal to one,
B等于1，浮点运算非常少。
B one, the floating point operation is very small.
但是你想在内存层级之间读取的数字位数呢？是一样的。
But how about the lumber bits you want to read between memory hierarchies? It's the same.
每次你尝试计算一个token时，你至少需要移动模型权重
Every time when you try to compute one token, you have to move at least the model weights
从GBM到SRM，然后你在GPU核心上执行计算。
from GBM to SRM, and you perform a competion GPU course.
这意味着如果你进行很多次计算，你只需要移动那一批数据一次。
That means that if you perform a lot of dance competition, you move that lumber bats once.
但如果你只进行很少的计算，你仍然要移动那一批数据一次。
But if you perform very few competition, you still move that lumber bats once,
当B变成1，S你也变成1时，在这个解码过程中会发生什么，
when B goes to one, S you go to one, what happens is that during this decoding process,
每次你进行一次传递时，你都要付出将权重从GBM移动到SRM的代价，
every time when you do a pass, you pay the cost of moving the weights from GBM to SRM,
但你实际计算的内容非常少。
but you only compute very little.
明白了吗？这就是为什么推测编码有效的问题吗？
Okay? That's a problem why speculative coding works?
因为我想我一周前讲过，推测之所以有效，是因为它
Because I think I talked about this one week ago, the reason speculating work is because it
可以减少步骤的数量。
can reduce the number of steps.
你会生成一个手动的token，因为你进行了推测。
You are going to generate a manual token, because you speculate.
你用一个小模型来推测，比如说五个token，然后把这五个token都交给
You use a small model to speculate, say, five tokens, and you give all these five tokens to
大的目标模型去做一次验证。
the large target arm to perform one verification.
当你进行这个验证时，你实际上花了很多代价去计算四个token。
And when you perform this verification, so you pay a lot of cost to compute four tokens.
但问题是，这个原始强度看起来并没有好多少
But the problem is, this original intensity don't look
因为低效操作在增加。
much better because the lamer ops is increasing.
比如说，如果你运气好，四个token都被接受了，
Say, if you get lucky and all the four tokens are accepted,
那你就大大提升了这个效率。
then you are making this equity much better.
你把在内存层级之间移动宽度的成本，分摊到了很多token上。
You are amortizing the cost of moving width between the memory hierarchy across many many tokens.
好的，这基本上就是从计算角度来看，为什么推测性编码可以加速。
Okay. So that is basically from a computational perspective why speculative coding can accelerate.
它分摊了内存移动的成本。
It amortize the memory movement cost.
但就像我说的，如果你不走运，比如你的接受率很低，
But like I said, if you are not lucky, if your acceptance rate is low, for example,
你的token被错误地提议了，目标端没有接受这些token，
your token was proposed wrong incorrectly and your target arm is not accepting these tokens,
那你就要付出额外的代价，因为你还要多付一次验证的成本。
then you are paying extra cost, because you are paying extra uh verification cost,
这会让你的推理变得更慢。
which we are making your inference even slower.
明白了吗？那就是推测编码。
Okay? That is specultive coding.
有什么问题吗？有的。
Any problem? Yeah.
为什么要用推测或者更大的子集？
Why speculative or large subset.
这是个非常好的问题，这其实也是现在人们正在研究的内容。
That's really great question. Is basically what people are doing research now.
是的，我们想在更大的B上应用推测编码，但问题是，
Yeah. We want to apply speculate coding at a larger B, but the problem is,
记住，推测编码的原理是你可以摊销内存移动的成本。
remember, the rationale of speculate encoding is that you amortize the memory movement cost.
但问题是，推测编码会消耗比没有推测编码更多的浮点运算。
But the problem is spectu encoding will consume more flops without a speculate code.
在更大的B下，你的系统不是受内存带宽限制，而是受计算能力限制，你在说，
At a larger B, your system is not memory bond with bond, it's computer bond, and you are saying,
我要付出更多的计算资源。
I'm going to pay more computer.
那么你就是在你的等价系统中加入了更多的计算机绑定。
Then you are adding more computer bond into your equiden system.
这就是为什么实际上很少有工作会这样做。这样说有道理吗？
That's why very few works actually do this. Does that make sense?
嗯，好。好的。不，我想我希望我能把这个联系到上周四的讲座，
Yeah. Okay. Okay. No, I think I hope I connect this back to the last Thursday's lecture,
这样你就能更好地理解为什么si degree从系统角度来看是有效的。
and you have a better understanding of why si degree works from a system perspective.
好的，那我们接下来进入今天的主要话题，可以吗？
Okay. Then let's move on to today's major topic, okay?
那么我们到底该如何解决这个问题呢？其中一个是批处理问题。
So how exactly, um, we solve that problem? One is the batching problem.
另一个是在大型数据库中的内存问题，对吧？
The other is the memory problem in large bases, okay?
所以我们要讨论的两种技术，基本上是连续批处理和付费
So the two techniques, we are going to talk about is basically continuous batching and pay
请大家注意。我们先从第一个开始。
your attention. Let's start with the first one.
好吗？还记得我们的问题吗？
Okay? So remember our problem, okay?
对于连续批处理，我们试图解决第一个不同的问题
For continuous batching, we try to solve the first problem that is different
提示的长度各不相同。
proms have different lens.
而且不同的提示有不同数量的不确定通用标记。
And different proms have different unknown number general tokens.
那么到底该如何进行批处理呢？
So how exactly batch them.
好的，首先，我认为我们需要可视化一下推理或解码的过程，
Okay. To begin, I think, we want to visualize, the arm inference or decoding,
呃，沿着时间的计算过程。
uh, commutation along time.
好的，所以你基本上可以看到这个图，对吧？
Okay. So here you basically can see this figure, right?
你有几个时间步，从T1到T8，对吧？
So you have a few times step from T one to T eight, okay?
基本上，你开始收到一个包含三个标记的请求，颜色是黄色，对吧？
And basically, you start receiving a request with three tokens, colour a yellow, okay?
在第一步，也就是这里。
And in the first step, which is this.
这一步你要计算预文件的竞争。
This step you compute prefile prefile compition.
然后当你完成预文件后，你要做的是权威解码。
And then once you finish prefile, what you do is you do authorizive decoding.
每次你解码一个，直到你解码到EOS，然后就完成了。
Every time you decode one, until you decode that EOS, and you finish.
这就像是实时可视化。明白吗？
This is like visualize on time. Okay?
现在，我想让你考虑一下说“不”，
Now, I want to think about say no,
我有多个请求进来了。
I have multiple requests coming.
我该如何实时计算呢？
How do I do compute on time?
明白吗？有一种方法，就是，比如这里，我有四个请求进来了，对吧？
Okay? One way, that is, um, here, I have four requests come in, right?
它们基本上有不同的首选长度。
They have different basically prefer lens.
第一个是三个，第二个是两个，依此类推，明白了吗？
The first one has three, second has two, et cetera, okay?
然后你为他们制作一批，好吗？
And you make them a batch, okay?
呃，我们稍后再谈自动批处理，但你可以想象一下，你可以把它做成一个
Uh, let's talk about auto batch later, but just think about, you can make it a
批次，然后把批次工作转发出去。
batch and forward a batches work.
然后你计算前缀R并开始生成。好的。
And you compute the prefiR and you start generating. Okay.
但是如果你看红色的图表，你会注意到第一个请求，
But if you look at the red graph, you will notice that the first request,
它只会生成两个标记，然后你到达结尾，
it will only generate two tokens, and then you enter the end,
辛普森，它只生成一个标记。
Simpson, it's only generate one token.
但是这个批次被第二个请求卡住了，第二个请求会生成很多标记。
But this batch was bott encked by the second request, which will generate a lot of tokens.
直到它在最后一个sems完成。
Until it finished at the last sems.
但我觉得从服务的角度来看，用户会发生什么？
But I think from a service perspective, what happened to the users?
实际上，对于第一个ers请求，它已经在时间步T6完成了。
So actually, for the first ers request, it already finished at the Time step T six.
但是因为这个请求和第二个请求被一起打包处理了。
But because this request was batched together with the second request.
所以第一个请求不会在结果中被观察到，直到整个批次完成为止，对吧？
So the first der is not going to observe in the results, right until the entire batch completes.
这实际上意味着，理想情况下，这个请求应该立即从
What it means, actually, ideally, okay, this request should immediately exit from
这个批次中退出，并将结果返回给用户。
that batch and go back to the user with the results.
但由于它们在计算图中被一起打包处理，它们必须反复经历
But because they are batting together in the computer graph, they have to repeatedly go through that
对每个请求都无所事事，对吗？
doing nothing for each request. Okay?
这就是传统批处理的一个例子，以及为什么
And this is one example of traditional batching and why
这个问题只会出现在RM，因为在之前，
this problem only happens for RM Because in previous,
在RM之前，人们都在服务什么样的模型？
before RM what kind of model people are serving?
比如说，非常典型的卷积神经网络，对吧？你不会遇到这个问题。
For example, uh, you know, very typical convolutionar networks, right? You don't have this problem.
为什么？因为如果你要解决这种场景，基本上就是一批图片，
Why? Because if you are going to solve this kind of scenes, you basically have a batch of images,
然后你把一批图片输入到网络里，所有图片都在同一个批次里，
and you throw a batch of images through network, and all the images in batches,
它们都以完全相同的速度完成，然后你返回结果。
they all follow exactly the same pace to finish and you return.
但在RM中，每个请求通常都有不确定数量的token，对吧？
But in RM, each request has undetermined lumber generally tokens, right?
这是RM独有的问题，明白吗？
That's the unique problem to RMs, okay?
你可以说，如果你用传统的批处理方式，我们会遇到很大的问题。
And you can say if you do this traditional batching, um, we have a big problem.
第一个问题当然就是，这个请求的延迟会被拖慢，对吧。
Like the first problem is, of course, the latency of this request you are delayed. Right.
第二个问题是，你可以看到，在过去两轮的竞争中，
A second problem is, you can see, during this left, during the competition over the last two wins,
所有这些地方都是气泡，这意味着我们的TP没有被充分利用。
all these sorts are bubbles, which means our TP is under utilized.
还有一个问题，我稍后会复查。
There's one more problem. I will review later.
好的。但总结来说，请求可能会在不同的迭代中完成，
Okay. But to summarize request may complete at different iterations in
因为生成的token数量不同，我们正面临着Ido GP循环的问题。
arms because different number of generate tokens, and we are facing Ido GP cycles.
第三点，基本上就是想象一下当我们计算这个批次时会发生什么。
The third point is basically imagine when we compute this batch, what will happen.
所以我们的用户会继续向我们的端点提交请求，
So our user is going to continue to submit requests to our endpoint,
而我们会在这里维护一个队列，请求排队。
and we are going to maintain a queue here, Queue in requests.
如果这个批次没有超出限制，那么我们必须
If this batch is not going to exceed then we have to
让队列中的后续请求继续等待，这基本上会导致
let the order requests in the queue to continue to wait, and that will basically increase
一个叫做水管线阻塞的问题。
a problem called hydro line blocking.
也就是说你的请求会被延迟。
That is your requests are being delayed.
我们来看看如何解决这个问题。
Let's see how we fix this problem.
我们解决这个问题的方法是可以把这种传统的批处理方式转换成
The way we fix the problem is that we can convert this kind of, like, traditional batching into
一种叫做连续批处理的新技术。
a new technique called continuous batching.
这种连续批处理是为arms设计的。
And this continue batching was designed for arms.
明白了吗？连续批处理的好处是我们有更高的GP利用率
Okay? And highlight was the benefit of continued batching that we have a higher GP radiation
而且新的请求可以立即开始。
and new request can start immediately.
老的请求一旦完成，就可以被推出去。
And an older request, once they finish, they can be basically pushed out.
它们可以立即被执行。
They can be excited immediately.
那么，我们来看看具体怎么做。
So, let's see how we do that.
好的，现在我们来逐步迭代地运行一下这个过程。
Okay. Now, let's run through this iteration by iteration. Okay.
所以这里我们有一个拉取请求，对吧。
So here we have a request to pull right.
这是我们的队列。
This is our queue.
好吗？我们正在监听。这是一个调查。
Okay? We are listening. This is a survey.
好的。想象一下你自己在户外。
Okay. And see. Imagine yourself is open air.
好的，你这里有一个队列，很多人在他们的浏览器上提交请求。
Okay, you have a queue here, a lot of requests on their browser, they are submitting requests.
一旦请求被提交，这个请求就会进入队列。
And once the submitted request, this request will go into a queue.
好的？所以这里我们观察到r1和r2。
Okay? So here we observe r1r2.
好的？然后我们有一个执行引擎，正在尝试执行任务，
Okay? And again, we have execution engine, which is trying to perform expedition,
这发生在GPU上。
and this happens on GPU.
这里，假设我们有一个GPU P，我们只能，嗯，服务于等于的基础。
And here, suppose we are pretty GPU P and we can only, um serve a basis equal to
最多三个，好吗？只是举个例子。
three at maximum, okay? Just example.
所以在第一次迭代中，我们可以看到在我们的队列里有两个请求，对吧？
So in the first iteration, we observe that in our Q, there are two requests, right?
所以我们基本上是把它们从CPU取到GPU，然后说，我们要把它们一起打包到Act里。
So we basically fetch them from CPU to GPU and we say, we are going to batch them together to Act.
好的？所以在这里，我的第一个问题是你是怎么进行批处理的。
Okay? So here, my first problem is how you basically batch this.
好的，我想看看这个并思考一下
Okay, I would like to look at this and think about
用30秒的时间，我去拿一下鼠标。不好意思。
for 30 seconds where I grab my mouse. Yeah, sorry.
好的，我们继续。
Okay, let's continue.
所以其实这真的很混乱。
So this is actually pretty messy, okay.
我之所以讲得这么详细，是因为我想确保你
The reason I do this in such detail is because I want to make sure you
明白这个批处理绝对不是简单的事情。
understand this batch is definitely non trivial.
为什么？因为想想看，如果这不是RM，只是一个普通的东西，
Why? Because consider if this is not RM if this is just a thing
这个批处理其实非常直接。
this batching is super straight forward.
基本上我的意思是，你观察两张图片，然后把这两张图片放到
Basically I'm saying you're observing two images, and you put these two images on
批次里，然后通过神经网络处理。
the batch and you go through the neural work.
而且这两张图片肯定会被重新调整到相同的尺寸，
And these two images is definitely, will be reshipped into the same size,
相同的分辨率，所以你不会有批处理的问题。
same resolution, so you don't have a batching problem.
但在这里，如果我们细分一下，好吧，我们实际操作一下。
But here, if we break it down, okay, let's be very hands on this.
如果我们决定对r1r2进行批处理，第一个遇到的问题是，它们很可能有不同的序列长度。
If we decide to batch r1r2, the first problem we facing is, they likely have different seqns.
但这里，我给了你一个很糟糕的例子，或者说有三个工作。
But here, I give you a pretty bad example or have three works.
但我们想一想，如果它们有不同数量的token，会出现什么问题。
But let's think about they have different umber tokens. Then what's the problem.
所以我们要通过第一个注意力层转发两个具有不同序列的请求
So we are going to forward two requests with different sequence through first attention
然后再通过MLP，对吗？
and then MLP, right?
那我问两个问题。
So let me ask two questions.
那我们可以把它们一起在注意力层做批处理吗？
So can we batch them together in attention?
我们可以，除非我们不能，除非我们基本上把较短的那个填充到长度等于四，对吧？
We can unless we cannot unless we basically pad the shorter one into six s equal to four, right?
因为注意力机制是依赖序列的。
Because attention is sequence dependent.
Attention必须按序列操作。
Atgen has to operate to.
如果你想把所有操作都批处理，就必须让它们有相同的序列长度。
And if you want to batch all the operators, you have to make them have the same sequence mass.
这意味着此时你实际上已经
Which means that at this moment, you are already basically
如果你做了这种填充，其实会损失一些算力，对吧？
losing some flops if you do this patty, right?
所以这是一个很多人在做决策时会考虑的问题，是否要批量处理这个问题。
So this is a decision that many serving frame how to fix to decide if you want to batch this a lot.
好吗？我稍后会回到这个话题，但现在让我们继续进入第二部分。就在这里。
Okay? I will come back to this later, but let's move forward to the second part. Okay, here.
假设你完成了注意力机制，这两个请求基本上就进入了MLP模块，对吧？
Suppose you finish your attention, and these two requests basically entering the MLP module, right?
那么你能在MP模块中批量处理这两个序列吗？
So can you bet these two sequence in MP module?
你可以，这很容易做到，对吧？
You can, that can be easily done, right?
因为在MLP模块中，它不是依赖于序列的。
Because in MLP module, it's not sequence dependent.
这一点非常重要，好吗？
And this is extremely important, okay?
所以在MLP模块中，
So in MLP module,
我甚至不关心序列维度。
I even don't care about sequence dimension.
对，因为在MLP中，如果你还记得计算过程，基本上每个token都会
Right. Because in MLP, if you still remember the computation, is basically each token will
有上投影和下投影。
be upper project and down project.
这意味着在MLP中，
Which means that in MLP,
在这个例子里，
I'm in this example,
实际上我得到的比特集等于六。
I'm actually getting a bit set equal to six.
它不是等于二。这说不通。
It's not equal to two. Doesn't make sense.
因为我把我的六个NS注册到之前的B乘以H里。现在，一旦我进入MLP，这个BNS，
Because I enroll my six NS into previously I B times times H. Now, once I enter MLP, this BNS,
我的MLP基本上无法处理这个S维度。
my MLP is basically I cannot speak to this S dimension.
基本上，MLP执行的是一种数学模式，即第一个维度是B乘以。
Basically, MLP is performing a math mode that is the first dimension is B times.
然后是H。这意味着在MLP中，计算是token独立的。
And set H. Which means that in MLP, the computation is token independent.
每个token都会执行自己的计算。
Each token will perform its own communication.
为什么这是一个非常重要的观察，我们将在下一页回顾它。
Why this is super important observation and we'll review it next slide.
但为了回答这个问题，为了进行批处理，你基本上是在观察
But to answer this question, in order to batch it, you are basically observing
两个请求，然后你把这两个请求合成一个批次，通过
two requests and you make this two requests one batch and you forward it through
RM转发以计算预填充。
the RM to compute the prefile.
在这个预填充竞争中，你要做的是在注意力机制中，
In this prefile competon, what you do is in the attention,
你可能会把它们一起填充到相同的长度，然后执行一次注意力操作。
you probably pad them together into the same lens, and you perform a attention.
在MLP中，你总是可以直接批处理，不需要做任何填充，这样就可以了。
In the MLP, you can always do batching without doing any padding. You are good.
好的，然后你看，我们进入了中间阶段一，好吗？
Okay. And then, see, we are entering our interim one, okay?
在我们的中间阶段一中，发生的事情是，我们完成了预填充，
In our interim one, what happened is, we finish prefill we
在这个批次中我们仍然有两个正在运行的请求，
still have two running requests in the batch,
我们现在将进入解码阶段，并且我们将要进行解码。
and we are going to transition into the decoding phase, and we are going to decode
为每个请求解码第一个标记。
the first token for each request.
与此同时，在我们的第三方，我们正在观察一个新的请求吗？
And meanwhile, on our third side, we are observing a new request?
那我再问你一个问题。
Then let me ask you another question.
那么在这种组合中，好吧，在临时竞争中，发生的事情是每个请求基本上
So in this combination, okay in the Interim one competon what happens is each request is basically
都在执行解码组合，对吧？
performing the decoding combination, right?
所以我的问题是，你们到底是如何将这两个解码批处理的？
So my question is, how you exactly batch these two decoding.
好的，让我们更深入一点，好吗？
Okay, let's step deeper, okay?
如果你看左边，情况也是一样的，对吧。
If you look at left hand side, same thing, right.
当我们进行解码时，我们首先会经过注意力机制和MLP。
When we perform decoding, we first go through attention the MLP.
那么对于MLP，我们可以批处理吗？
So for MLP, can we batch?
可以，正如我刚才说的，MLP是对每个token独立的。
Yes, like I said, the MLP is token independent.
那里面有什么问题吗？
So what's the bad inside?
有两个，对吧？因为我们是在比较两个token。
Two, right? Because we are comparing two tokens.
好的。但对于注意力机制，我们可以批处理吗？
Okay. But for attention, can we batch.
不行，因为这里有一个不好的例子。
No, because here is a bad example.
假设第一个有一个token，第二个有三个token，那么你就不能批处理，因为它们
Assuming the first has first token, second half three tokens, then you cannot batch because they
基本上是在执行不同的计算。
basically are performing different competition.
一个是在关注前面的三个token，另一个是在关注前面的两个token。
One is attending to previous three tokens and the other is attending to previous two tokens.
它们的形状不同，不能批处理。
Their ship are different. You cannot batch.
好吗？如果你想击球，你就得穿护具，而如果你穿了护具，你就输了，对吧？
Okay? If you want to bat, you have to pad, and if you pad, you lose, right?
所以本质上，在今天的框架下，当你进行这种竞争时，
So essentially in today's framework, when you do this kind of competition,
它比你想象的要复杂得多。
it's much more complexe than your thought.
这不像你把一批数据直接输入petty然后得到结果那么简单。
It's not like you forwarding a batch through petty and you get results.
他们做的基本上是，对tinin和MLP进行非常详细的拆解，
And what they do is basically, they do very detailed breakdown for tinin and MLP,
并且他们为十个MLP执行不同的击球策略。
and they perform in different batting strategy for ten MLP.
那么，在这种情况下，我们该怎么办？
Okay. So in this case, what do we do?
比如说，在今天的服务框架VIM中，
For example, in today's um, serving framework VIM,
他们会为每个序列独立执行tensing内核，
they will basically execute the tensing kernels for each sequence independently without
而不是用一个批次，因为他们想节省流量。
one batch because they want to save flows.
但是一旦他们完成了分组，他们会把所有的token放到
But once they finish the tenting, they are going to put all tokens into
一个大批次里，然后执行一个MLP。
one big batch and perform an MLP.
接着在下一层，他们基本上会把一个批次拆开，
And then unter the next layer, they are going to basically break down a batch,
分别执行不同的内核，然后再重新批量处理，批量又批量。
perform separate kernels, and then batching together, and then batch batch and batch batch.
你明白我的意思了吗？好吧，这真的很复杂，好吗？
You got me right? Okay. It's very complicated, okay?
你为什么要这么做？我们来看一下Eteren三。
Why did you do that? Let's see Eteren three.
但在我讲E三之前，让我们做一个心理实验。
But before I move to eat three, let's perform a mental experiment.
如果我们采用传统的批处理，会发生什么？
What would happen if we do traditional batching.
好的，现在我们进入interim二，对吧？
Okay. So now, we move to interim two, right?
因为在interim一，如果我们按照传统的批处理方式，
Because at interim one, if we follow traditional batching,
我们已经决定发起一批两个请求，并且我们继续解码
we already decided to issue a batch of two requests, and we continue to decode
当前正在运行批次的下一个token。
next token for the current running batch.
但在中间阶段二，发生的情况是我们继续观察到另外两个请求RF和FL。
But at interim two, what happens is we continue to observe another two requests RF and FL.
但如果我们遵循传统的批处理方式，问题是，嗯，我们发出这一批，
But if we follow traditional batching, the problem is um, we issue this batch,
然后我们必须等这一批完成，然后再取下一批，
and we have to wait for this batch to finish, and then we take another batch,
你可以想象这样有多糟糕，对吧？
you can imagine how bad this is, right?
基本上，当你在运行r1r2时，你的队列在增加。队列的大小在增加。
Basically, when you are running r1r2, your queue is increasing. The size is increasing.
有更多的请求到达，但你基本上无法添加
A lot of more requests are arrival but arriving, but you are not able to basically add
或者说无法向当前正在运行的批次中添加任何内容。
or basically add anything into the current running batch.
好吗？很棒。在运行连续批处理的实习生之前，我们来总结一下。
Okay? Cool. To summarize before running interns for continuous batching,
我想总结一下传统批处理的缺点。
I want to summarize the drawbacks or traditional batching.
正如你所看到的，在传统批处理方式中，一旦你发出一个批次，你就需要
So as you can see, in traditional batting, once you issue a batch, you are going to
等待这个批次完成。
wait for that batch to complete.
基本上，如果你这样做，问题就在于队列中的请求无法进入，对吧？
So basically, if you do this, the issue is that request in the queue they cannot enter, right?
而且提前完成的请求也无法退出。
And also request finished early cannot exit.
在这个例子中，你可以看到这个请求已经到达了US，这意味着它本应该退出。
In this example, you see this request to it already hit US, which means that it should be exited.
但是，你知道，在我之前的示意图中，
But, you know, in my previous illustrating,
我展示了你无法让这个批次中的请求退出。
I showed that you cannot exit this batch.
正因为如此，由于每个请求所需的通用令牌数量不同，GPO 可能会处于空闲状态。
And because of this, GPO could be idle due to a different number of general tokens per request.
接下来让我们看看连续批处理是如何解决这个问题的。
Then let's see how continuous batching addresses this problem.
好吗？所以目前我们的状态是在第一步，我们有一个正在运行的一批或两批任务。
Okay? So still, this is our current status at one, where we have a running batch or two.
我们批次中的每个请求已经解码了一个标记，这时我们观察到一个新请求。
Each request in our batch already decoded one token and we observe a new request.
那么在连续批处理的情况下会发生什么呢？
So what will happen in continuous batching is that in continuous batching,
只要，比如说，空间允许，只要我们的策略允许，
as long as, for example, space allows, as long as our policy allows,
我们会立刻接收请求R3，并把R3加入正在运行的批次中。
we are going to immediately pick up the request R three and put R three into the running batch.
好的，我们不会等待。也就是说，我们不会让批处理成为实体，
Okay, we're not waiting. That is, we're not making batting entity,
我们让请求成为实体，迭代成为实体。
we are making requests entity, iterating entity.
所以只要有空间，我们就会立即接收请求并把它放入队列中。
So as long as space allows, we are going to immediately pick up or request and put that into queue.
但在这里你会遇到一个非常棘手的问题。
But here you are facing a very difficult problem.
什么问题呢？如果你这样做，如果你接收了R3，对吧？
What's the problem? If you do this, if you pick up R three, right?
然后你把cary放进了一个运行中的批次里。
And you put cary into a running badge.
你现在面临的问题是，你明白我试图说明的意思吗？
You are facing a problem that is you see what I try to illustrate.
好吗？所以这里，三，只是进入了电池。
Okay? So here, three, just enter the battery.
记住，推理时，请求的第零步总是执行预填充。
Remember, inference, the first step the zero step for request is always doing pre fill.
但是在这里，R1和R2，它们是推理的不同状态。
But here, R one and R two, they are different states of the inference.
它们在解码，它们在解码。
They are decoding they are decoding.
所以这里你的意思是，我正在创建一个批次，其中有些请求需要执行
So here you are saying I'm making a batch where some requests need to perform
预填充，但有些请求需要执行解码。
prefill but some requests need to perform decoding.
这样说有道理吗？这完全是不同的计算，对吧？
Does that make sense? This is a totally different competion, right?
一个就像你在观察一样。
One is like you observe to.
另一个就像你在解码，对吗？
The other is like you are decoding, right?
表面上看这张图，这根本不是batchb，对吧？
Superficially if you look at this picture, this is not batchb at all, right?
计算图是不同的。
Be computation graph is different.
但我们再深入一步。
But again, let's step deeper.
我来解释为什么这是蔬菜。
I explain to you why this is vegetable.
我们再把它分解一下。
Again, let's break it down.
计算由两部分组成，注意力和MLP。
The computation composed of two parts, attention and MLP.
好吗？如果你想让这三个请求的计算一起运行，
Okay? So if you want to make these three request computation run together,
我们一个一个来看，好吗？
we look at one by one, okay?
那么对于它们的注意力部分，我们能把它们批处理吗？
So for their attention, can we batch them?
从根本上说我们做不到，因为一个是在处理一个token，另一个是在处理多个token。
Fundamentally we cannot because one is attending to one token attend to operate tokens.
另一个是三个token，你需要对神经网络进行批量处理。
The other is three tokens, you need to perform a batch pass of the neural network.
这意味着它们不是蔬菜，这似乎不对。
Which means that they are not a vegetable, and this seems wrong.
如果它们不是蔬菜，为什么要把它们放在一起？
If they are not vegetable why are putting them together.
但实际上，如果你更注意细节，
But in fact, if you pay more attention to detail,
你会发现，如果你看像MLP，我们能批量处理它们吗？
you'll find that if you look like MLP, can we batch them?
是的，对于MLP，我们可以批量处理它们。
Yes, for MLP, we can batch them.
即使是在预处理和解码时，我们也可以把MLP放到一次批量运行的新网络中。
Even for prefer and decoding, we can put the MLP into one single battered run new network.
为什么？因为就像我说的，无论是在预处理还是解码中，MLP总是与token独立的。
Why? Because like I said, no matter in prefer decoding, the MLP is always token independent.
它是自己对token进行操作的。
It performs on the tokens by itself.
好吗？这意味着按照这个拆分方式，不会得到新的内部结构。
Okay? That means that with this breakdown, will not get a new inside.
也就是说，即使我们把prefer和cooling放到同一批次里，
That is, even if we put prefer and cooling into the same batch,
我们实际上至少可以把它们的MLP合并处理。
we can actually at least batch their MLP.
好吗？现在，我想提醒你们上周我们做了什么，好吗？
Okay? Now, I want to remind you what we did last week, okay?
我记得我们为RM做了flops的计算，并且统计了tensing和MLP中的flops数量。
I think we run the flops calculation for RMs, and we count the number of flops in a tensing and MLP.
我希望你们还记得那个百分比。
I hope you still remember the percentage.
那么，RM中哪个部分占用了最多的flops？
So which component in RM occupy the most flops?
大多数情况下是MLP，对吧？
MLP in most cases, okay?
除非你有一个超级长的序列，对吗？
Unless you have a super long sequence ance, right?
但在大多数情况下，你实际上只有中等或较短的序列。
But in most cases, you have actually medium to low sequenans.
这意味着如果你这么做，是的，你的系统会变得更复杂。
Which means that if you do this, yes, your system is going to be more complicated.
但实际上你能获得很多好处。
But you actually can win a lot.
为什么？因为就像我说的，在大多数请求和大多数序列场景下，
Why? Because like I said, in most requests in most sequence ans regime,
那个MLP会占用你90%的计算量，如果你能把它批量处理，你就赢了，对吧？
that MLP is going to take 90% of your flops, and if you are able to batch it, you win, right?
至于注意力机制，是的，你无法批量处理它，但没关系，因为它只占10%的计算量。
And for attention, yes, you are not able to batch it, but it's fine because it's only 10% of flops.
我们来算一下，如果按顺序处理是否可行。
Let's just compute if the sequential is okay.
好吗？所以这是最重要的见解，来自于连续批处理。
Okay? So this is the biggest insight, taken from continuous batching.
现在你明白了。
And now you understand.
好吗？那为什么人们会发现这种形式呢？
Okay? So why people discover this form?
因为在所有像petrogTener flow这样的框架出现之前，他们并不了解这种方式。
Because before all frameworks like petrogTener flow, they don't understand this kind of
就像他们在这个层面上没有被详细处理一样。
like they are not handled in detail at this level.
所以基本上他们把计算机当作静态的，然后通过新网络进行转发。
So basically they treat the computer as static and they forward about through the new network.
明白了吗？这就是为什么在C批处理之前，如果人们把请求放到petrog或者Tinder flow里，
Okay? That's why before C batching, if people put the request into petrog or into Tinder flow,
你是得不到很高的效率的。
you are not going to get great efficiency.
但后来，我记得大约一年半前在OSDI 2023上有一篇论文发表，
But later, I think there's a paper published in OSDI 2023, basically 1.5 years ago,
他们提出了一种技术，能够把这个问题分解成
they discourage technique, and they are able to break this down into
MLP，并且对图的不同部分采用不同的批处理策略。明白了吗？嗯。
MLP and they do different batching strategy for different parts of the graph. Okay. Yeah.
抱歉。
Sorry.
嗯，是的，这是个很好的问题。
Uh huh. Yes, that's a really good question.
这是个很好的问题。所以你的意思是如果我们批处理的话
That's a really good question. So you're saying if we batch
rthter prefer 和 Ring 更喜欢 MLP，因为动脉非常长，
the MLP of rthter prefer and Ring together, because artery is super long,
那么 r1r2 就会被延迟。
then r1r2 is going to be delayed.
这个问题问得很好。我会讲到这个。
Really good question. I'm going to cover that.
好吗？是的，我在这方面发表过论文。
Okay? Yeah, I publish paper on that. Yeah.
为了解决这个问题。是的，我可以再多讲一些。
To solve that problem. Yeah. I can give you more.
这叫做前缀解码分离。
It's called prefiw decode disaggregation.
这叫做分离式预防解码。
It's called disaggregated prevent decoding.
这是目前存储超大数据的默认技术。
That is the default technique today for storing really large bits.
我觉得你已经发现了这个问题。
And I think you already spotted that problem.
但我们先把这个问题讲完。好的，现在，
But let's finish this problem. Okay. And now,
你明白条件批处理的本质，对吧？
you understand the essence of condition batching, right?
所以这是条件批处理的第一个非常好的好处，但还有更多。
So this is the first, very good benefit of condi batching, but there are more.
为什么？因为现在你变得更加灵活了，
Why? Because now you become more flexible,
以前，你总是运行静态批处理，并且等待那个批次完成。
Previously, you always run static batch and you wait for that batch to finish.
现在因为你能够把这个组合图分解成一个小型的MLP，
And now because you are able to break this cobion graph into a tinging MLP and
你可以采用不同的批处理策略。
you do different batching strategy.
所以你可以更加灵活。
So you can be more flexible.
那么我说的灵活性是什么意思呢？
So what do I mean by flexibility?
在这里，你总是可以接收一个新的请求并把它加入到一个批次中，
So here, you can always pick up a new request and put it into a batch,
并且让它和其他正在解码的批次一起运行。
and make it running with other ongoing batches, which are in decoding.
你还可以做另一件事，比如说，如果艺术品完成了，好吧，我刚刚搞定了。
And you can also do another thing that is say, if the art is finished, okay, I just aced it.
是的，我会把它还给用户。
Yeah, I just return it to users.
这就是为什么我会留出另一个存储点，从队列中接收新的请求，对吧？
And that's why leave another store for me to pick up another request from the queue, right?
这大大解决了halo行阻塞的问题，因为如果你对比传统批处理，
And this greatly address the halo line blocking because if you compare traditional batching,
和连续批处理。
and continuous batching.
传统批处理中，正在运行的批次必须等待
What happens is in traditional batching, that running batch has to wait
最慢的请求完成。
for the slowest request to finish.
但在连续批处理中，因为批处理策略本质上是不同的，
But in continuous batching, because the batching strategy are fundamentally different,
我会不断接收新的请求。
I'm going to always pick up a new request.
我会用不同的方式批处理它们在MLP上的注意力。
I batch their attention on MLP differently.
好吗？这样你就可以看到，在传统批处理方式下，
Okay? And in that way, you can see at its sp in traditional batching,
动脉在等待，但在连续批处理下，动脉会进入
artery is waiting, but in continuous batching, artery is going to enter
电池并开始竞争。
the battery and start competition.
从用户的角度来看，他们基本上会体验到更低的延迟，好吗？
And from a user's perspective, they will basically experience a much lower latency, okay?
我会继续把这个讲完，好吗。
And I will continue to finish this, okay.
所以在这一步，你正在计算首选ASR和解码环境在两个，
So at this step, you are computing the prefer ASR and decoding environment at two,
但你观察到一个或两个请求，对吧？
but you observe one er two request, right?
你要做的就是继续选择请求。
And what you do is you continue to pick up to request.
所以在这里，很明显你不能选择，因为就像我说的，
So here, apparently, you cannot pick up because like I said,
这个TP只有能力支持请求。
this TP only have capacity to support request.
所以你要做的是观察到请求二正在命中我们。
So what you do is you observe that two is hitting US.
所以你基本上退出那个请求，返回给用户。
So you basically exit that request, return to users.
对吧？然后你立刻接手我们的请求。
Right? And you pick up our immediately.
在这个批次中，发生的情况是R三，
In this batch, what happens is R three,
R一基本上进入了解码阶段，但R四在做预处理。
R one are basically entering decoding, but R four is doing pre few.
你基本上分别处理它们的注意力核，但你把MLP的通信合并成
You basically act their attention kernel separately, but you batch the MLP communication into
一个大批次，以利用diplls。
one big batch to leverage diplls.
明白了吗？同样的道理，对吧？
Okay? And same thing, right?
所以同样的，你一直这样做，直到你观察到没有请求为止。
So same thing, you keep doing this until you observe no requests.
好的，总结一下，好吗？
Okay. To summarize, okay?
所以连续批处理非常聪明，因为它能更高效地处理提前完成和低速率的请求。
So continuous batching is really smart because it handles early finished and
而且显然，由于你能够组成更大的批次，所以可以提升你的吞吐量。
little rate requests more efficiently.
关键的见解是，注意力机制只消耗很小比例的计算量。
And apparently because you are able to make a bigger batch size, so you can improve your tion.
至少对于短到中等长度的序列来说是这样。
And the key insight here is attention consumes small percentage of flops,
并且MLP核对序列长度这个维度是无关的。
Okay, at least for short to medium six lengths.
所以你总是可以把transformer里的各种计算批量处理。
And MLP kernels are agnostic to the six dimension.
更倾向于把解码合并成一个大批次来提升吞吐量。
So you can always batch whatever kind of computation in transformer
好的，有关于连续批处理的问题吗？很好。
prefer decoding into one big batch to improve don.
没问题。之前我还以为可以给你们留个作业。
Okay. Any question for continuous batching? Cool.
We are good. Previously, I thought I could make a homework for you to
写连接代码，但我现在没有时间。
write connection, but I don't have time.
不过我认为这是一个很好的练习，因为你必须能够实现
But I think this is a pretty good practice, because you have to be able to implement
这种服务器-客户端架构，这也是我们今天默认的架构。
this server client architecture, which is a default here today.
但也许我们下次再做这个吧。
But maybe let's do that next time.
那么我们来试着解决第二个问题。
Then let's try to address the second problem.
我认为第二个问题更加难以理解，很多人都发现不了这个问题。
I think a second problem is even more opaque and many people they cannot discover this problem.
它隐藏在更底层。
It's hidden in a lower layer.
我们来看看这个问题是什么，好吗？
Let's see what's the problem, okay?
那么，在推理过程中，让我再重复一遍，对吧？
So so in inference process, let me repeat, right?
所以M有一个独特的组件，叫做KB缓存，对吗？
So M has a unique component, which is called KB catch, right?
嗯，所以基本上，在处理新标记时，模型实际上需要
Um, so basically, in processing new tokens, the model actually needs to
不仅需要当前标记的表示，还需要之前标记的表示，
not only the repent of the current token, it also needs the repenting of the previous tokens,
而这种表示基本上就是KB缓存。
and that rent is basically the KB cache.
明白了吗？所以之前标记的这些状态应该保存在内存中，
Okay? So this states of previous tokens should be kept in memory,
这基本上就叫做KB缓存。
and this is basically called KB catch.
明白了吗？比如说，在这个例子里，一个新标记，比如“未来”，对吧？
Okay? So so a new token, for example, in this example, the future uh the future comes, right?
所以除了当前的标记本身，我们还需要关注所有之前标记的KB缓存，
So besides the token itself, we also need to attend to all the KB caches
对吧？
of the previous tokens, right?
所以我们基本上会持续关注之前的KB缓存，然后生成下一个标记。
So we basically keep attending to the previous KB catch and we generate next token.
好的，总结一下刚才说的内容。
Okay. So basically, to recap a little bit, okay.
基本上，KV缓存是一个用于存储标记中间向量表示的内存空间。
So basically KV catch is a memory space to store the intermediate vector representations of tokens.
我们其实可以把它理解为一个工作集，而不是缓存。
And um, and basically, we can understand it as a working set rather than a catch.
所以我想纠正一下这个词，好吗？
So I want to correct this word, okay?
这个领域的人都叫它缓存，但你们可能知道
People in this field, they call this catch, but you probably know what
缓存的正式定义是什么。
is the formal definition of catch.
缓存是你可能命中也可能不命中的东西。
So catch is something that you can hit or may not hit.
但在这个例子里，它其实不是缓存，因为它总是会被命中，对吧？
But in this example, it is not a cache why because it'll always be hit, right?
这个名字有点奇怪，因为是做硬件的人起的，
Um I had a weird name because the name was come up with by machinery people,
不是系统领域的人，所以不严谨。
not system people. It's not rigorous.
但我们就这样理解它吧，好吗？
But let's just understand it that way, okay?
这是百分之百的隐藏缓存，好吗？所以
This is 100% hid cache, okay? So
如果你把记忆看作一种模式，其实有两种模式，对吧？
So if you look at the memories, kind of like a pattern, there are two patterns, right?
一种是 QVC 的大小会动态增长。
One is, the size of the QVC what dynamic grows.
因为随着你的解码过程继续，QB 缓存的大小
Because as your decoding continues, the size of the QB cash
与请求对应的缓存也会增长。
corresponding to the request is going to grow.
但在某个时刻，它会缩小。
But at some point, it will shrink.
为什么？因为那个请求已经结束了。
Why? Because that requests finishing.
并且因为我们应用了条件批处理。
And because we apply conditions batching.
一旦那个请求结束，我们就会执行请求，
Once that request is finished, we are going to act request,
把它返回给用户，然后释放对应的内存空间
return it to users, and we are going to release the memory space corresponding
到该请求的Qcache中。
to the Qcache of that request.
基本上，从我们的请求角度来看，QB缓存的内存就是这样工作的。
Basically, from our request perspective, the memory of the QB caches like this it inarly
女孩，然后突然就变了。明白吗？
girl and then suddenly becomes. Okay?
这样说有道理吗？好的，明白了。那么接下来，
Does that make sense? Okay. Cool. Okay, so with that,
嗯，呃，我们可以直接把Kcatch放到内存里，对吧？
um, uh, we can just put K catch in memory, right?
那么我们为什么要关心这些缓存呢？
So why do we care about these catches?
好的，接下来我要给大家展示今天讲座中最重要的幻灯片之一。
Okay. And next, I'm going to give you one of the most important slides for today's lecture.
那么为什么QBCach很重要呢？
So why QBCach matters.
好，如果我告诉你，其实高效地管理Kcatch在
Okay. So what if I tell you that basically efficient management of Kcatch in
内存中实际上可以提升AM服务的吞吐量。
memory can actually improve the AM service throughput.
这其实挺反直觉的，对吧。
This is pretty counterintuitive, right.
为什么管理内存可以提升吞吐量。
Why managing memory can improve throughput.
但事实就是这样。明白吗？我们来看一下，我们运行一个130亿参数的模型。
But this is the case. Okay? So let's see, we run a 13 billion model.
嗯，40G的GPU，这就是A100，对吧，
Um, 40 gigaGPU, this is A 100 right,
40G内存，我们基本上是在运行一个130亿参数的ama模型。
40 giga memory, and we are basically running a 13 billion ama.
如果你看这个分解，因为我们有130亿个参数，
So if you look at this breakdown, because we have 13 billion parameters,
所以我们首先会消耗26G来存储权重，对吧，乘以二，明白吗？
so we are going to first consume 26 giga to store we, right time two, okay?
另外，我们还有一小块区域，主要用来生成那些中间状态。
And in addition, we have a small other area which will basically generate those intermediate states.
但因为这是推理，我们不需要存储它们。
But because it's inference, we don't have to store them.
一旦生成了这些状态，我们就把它们丢弃。
Once we generate the we throw them away.
我们转到下一层。所以这是一个小区域。
We forward to next layer. So it's a small area.
基本上，如果你看粉色部分，基本上就是剩下的内存，
So basically, uh, if you look at the pink part, is basically the rest of memory that is
用于存储推理时的QB案例。
used to store QB case for inference.
所以，我们基本上有一条曲线图，X轴是运行中的字节大小。
So, we basically have a curve plot where um, the X access is running byte size.
连续批处理会不断将请求加入批次中。
Continuous batching continue to pick up requests into the batch.
所以X轴是当前批次的字节大小，也就是你同时运行的
So the X access is the running batch bite size, which is the number of
请求数量。
requests you are running concurrently.
Y轴是内存使用量。
Where access is the memory usage.
所以你的起点是26。
So your starting point is 26.
为什么？因为你已经消耗了26条主干道。
Why? Because you already consuming 26 motorways.
那么如果你继续像我说的那样，接收更多要在GPU上运行的请求，
Then if you continue to pick up more requests to run on the GPU like I said,
QV模式会继续增长然后收缩。
the QV pattern will continue to grow and then shrink.
但现在假设我们正在运行spatch，并且持续增加bite size。
But now let's assume we are running spatch we continue to increase bite size.
那么你的内存曲线会像这样。
Then your memory curve will be looking like this.
所以你会持续增长。
So you will continue to grow.
一旦你接收请求，你会为bias消耗一些内存。
Once you pick up request, you consume some memory for bias.
在某个时刻，你会达到40G。
And at some point, you are going to kit 40 giga.
那意味着你的内存已经满了。
That means that full you're full on memory.
好吗？好，你可能会好奇为什么我画了这个滚动条，但如果你做一个预测，
Okay? Okay, you probably wonder why I draw this scroll, but if you do a projection,
你会发现，在某个时刻，好吗？我正在服务。
you'll find that at some point, okay? I'm serving.
这个运行的批量大小受内存大小的限制。
This running bitty size is limited by memory size.
如果你的内存不够大，你就无法容纳更大的批量大小。
If you don't have enough memory, you are not going to accommodate
那么，为什么这很重要呢？
a larger bit size. So why is this important?
是的，没错，因为这是GPU。
Yeah, exactly, because this is GPU.
只要你的GPU计算没有成为瓶颈，你就可以继续增加你的批量大小，
As long as your GPU compute is not bottleneck, you can continue to increase your bad size,
并且你的计算将在相同的时间内完成，
and your commutation is going to finish in the same amount of time,
即使你有更大的批量大小。
even if you have a larger bite size.
这意味着在推理服务中，基本上你的工作负载会受到内存瓶颈的限制。
Which means that in serving, basically, your workload becomes memory bottlenecked.
你首先会遇到内存瓶颈，然后才会遇到计算瓶颈。
You first hit the bottleneck memory, and then you hit the bottnFlops.
明白了吗？所以假设我们有一种方法，基本上可以把这条绿色曲线从陡峭的曲线变得平缓。
Okay? So suppose if we have a way to basically flatten this green curve from this pretty steep curve
变成了一个稍微更好看的曲线，就是这个蓝色的。
into a slightly more flattering curve, this blue one.
这意味着每次我们在运行批次中加入一个新请求时，我的曲线
That means that every time we add a new request into running batch my curve
只会增加一点点，增长速度比之前的曲线慢很多。
is only going to increase a little bit, much slower than previous curve.
然后如果你继续沿着这条曲线走，直到我碰到40G内存的限制，你可以看到，
Then if you continue to trouble this curve until I hit the 40 giga memory limit, you can see,
如果我足够聪明地画出那条曲线，我再做一次垂直投影，
I do another vertical projection if I'm smart enough to make that curve,
那么我就可以运行40个批次。
then I can run running bats of 40.
问题在于GPU的计算量其实更少了。
The problem is GPUs computation is looking at less.
基本上，吞吐量是批次大小的函数。
Basically, the throughput is a function of bite size.
所以如果你能够更好地利用GPU，那么当你增加批次大小时，GPU的利用率
So if you are able to uti GPU better, then your GPO is not going
并不会显著提升，这意味着运行一个批次
to increase significantly if you increase the bite size, which means that running a bat
等于八并且运行速度等于四十时，它们花费的时间是一样的。
equal to eight and running at equal to 40, they take same amount of time.
但因为你运行的电池等于四十，你每秒会产生更多的令牌。
But because you are running a battery equal to 40, you are going to produce more tokens per second.
因此，如果你再画一条水平曲线，你的吞吐量会增加。
Therefore, your throughput, if you draw another horizontal curve,
你会发现，吞吐量几乎增加了四倍。
you say, the throughput increase almost four times.
好的，这其实是一个更深层次的见解。
Okay. And this is a pretty deeper inside.
如果你不这样做，你可能永远不会注意到这一点。
If you don't do this, you probably never observe this.
这是我的论文，VM。
And this is my paper, VM.
显然，我们之所以这样做，是因为我们是GPU四。
Apparently, the reason we did this is because we are GPU four.
假设你是谷歌，你用很多GPU在处理大量请求，
Consider you are Google and you are serving a lot of requests using a lot of GPS,
你永远不会注意到这一点，因为你没有遇到内存瓶颈。
you are never observing this because you are not hitting that memory of the neck.
好吗？我们观察到这一点，然后我们基本上构建了一个叫做VM的系统，这个VM基本上就是利用
Okay? And we observe this and we basically build a system called VM, and this VM basically using
这个技巧来高效地管理
this trick to efficiently manage
P内存，并将P内存转化为更高的吞吐量。
P memory and convert that P memory into improved throughput.
明白了吗？现在你了解了内部原理。
Okay? Now, you understand the inside.
那么它到底是怎么做到的呢？
So how exactly did that?
我们来深入了解一下这个技术。
Let's dive into the technique.
那么，为什么现有的系统在内存上效率低下呢？
So basically why existing systems there memory inefficient, okay?
这是使用以前系统时KV缓存的一个快照。
So so this is a snapshot of the KV catch when using a previous system, okay?
在这里我们发现了三种类型的内存浪费。
So where we find out three types of memory waste.
第一种是预留。
So the first is reservation.
也就是说你会保存很多内存存储，对吧，每个存储基本上都保存着
So which means that you hold many memory stores, right, and each story basically saives
每个token的QV缓存，对吗？
the QV cache for each token, okay?
第一种宽度类型是物理预留。那么什么是retbon？
So, the first type of width is physical reserviion. So what is retbon?
Retbon的意思是那些此刻没有被使用的词，
Rtobon means that those words that are not used at this moment,
但在之后的序列中会被使用。
but will be used um for that sequence in the future.
为什么会有这种情况？
Why why there is such a case?
因为你通常是一个一个地处理。
Because you're talking generally one by one.
所以当你为那个token分配内存以存储keV时，你可以先让分配器给你，
So when you allocate memory to see the keV for that token, you can first ask the allocator to give,
呃，我打算生成100个token。
uh, I'm going to generate 100 tokens.
那你为什么不直接给我100个呢，对吧？
Why don't you just give me 100, right?
但是一旦你请求了这100个，在你请求的那一刻，你就被分配了这100个槽位。
But once you ask for this 100, at the moment you ask you are granted this 100 slots.
实际上你并没有生成100个token。
You're actually not generating 100 tokens.
这就叫做报应，明白吗？
So that's called retribution, okay.
所以，这里中间的这些词。
So so here these words in the middle.
它们被保留了，因为在当前步骤并没有存储任何token，
Okay, they are reserved because they don't store any token at the current step
在当前解码步骤没有存储，但会用于存储未来的token。
at the current deconing step, but will be used to store, uh like future tokens.
明白了吗？第二种基本上被称为，这是一个保留token。
Okay? So the second is basically called, um, this is a reserved token.
你看到了吧。所以它最终会被使用，但在当前步骤不会被用到，明白吗？
You see that right. So it will be used eventually but not used at the current step. Okay?
第二种基本上被称为，嗯，
The second is basically called, um,
我希望你学过操作系统课程，对吧？你知道这个，对吧？
I hope you have taken operating system class, right? You know this right?
这被称为内部碎片化，意思是那些单词被分配了，
It's called internal fragmentation, which means that those words
但实际上永远不会被使用。
allocated for sequence, but will never be used.
那些都是已经分配的。
That is all allocated.
好的。这种情况发生是因为序列的输出长度事先是未知的。
Okay. So this happens because the output length of the sequence is not known or priory.
所以，实际上你根本不知道要分配多少，好吗？
So, in fact, you don't know how much to allocate at all, okay?
所以你只能尝试一下。
So you just try.
比如说，我就分配了，比如说，最大序列长度，
For example, I just allocate, for example, the maximum sequence length,
我希望我的序列会用到那么多的token，但实际上它会提前结束，
and I hope my sequence is going to use that many tokens, but in fact, it will exceed
在用完最大信号之前就结束了。
earlier than using the maximum signals.
这就是所谓的内部碎片化。
So this is what calls internal fragmentation.
当然，最后你会遇到一些外部碎片问题，
And, of course, finally, you have some sort of external fragmentation that is because you
因为你为不同的请求分配了不同的空间，中间就会产生一些碎片，
allocate different different sorts to different requests and there are some fragmentation between,
而你无法利用这些碎片空间。
and you're not able to use this kind of thing.
那么，这个问题到底有多严重呢？
So so how severe this is, okay?
如果你看看这个内存分布情况，
So if you look at this, memory breakdown, okay?
内存浪费其实非常严重。
The memory waste is very significant.
基本上，在这个分析中，针对不同的内存管理方案，
So basically in this profile, data with different memory management schemes,
我们发现只有20%到30%的缓存实际上被用来存储token ss。
we observe only 20 to 30% of kebic ash is actually utilized to store the token ss.
剩下的空间基本上都被浪费在了保留、
The rest of the space is basically being wasted for reservation for
内部碎片和外部碎片上。
internal and external fragmentation.
好吗？基本上我们做的就是，基本上试图让我们
Okay? And basically what we do is, we basically, try to leave that we
基本上试图让那条绿色的进度条一直保持到99%。
basically try to leave that green ban all the way to 99%.
好吗？也就是说，所有的内存最终都会被用来保存tokens。
Okay? That is all the memory will be eventually utilized to save tokens.
我觉得在这一点上，如果你非常熟悉
And I think at this point, you already, if you are very familiar
操作系统中的内存管理，你可能已经知道我们的技巧是什么了，对吧？
with memory management in operating systems, you probably know what's our trick, right?
基本上你可以用所谓的虚拟内存，好吗，用页表。
It's basically you can use a so called virtual memory, okay, use page tables.
但是你必须在机器学习系统中做这件事。
Okay. But you have to do this machine learning systems.
这基本上就是我们试图把你在操作系统中学到的知识和
Okay, that is basically like we try to connect the dots, what you have learned in OS and
我们今天在紧急系统中所做的事情联系起来。
what we are doing today emergency systems.
所以现在你明白问题了。那么解决方案是什么呢？
So now you understand the problem. So what's the solution?
这是一个非常古老的问题，对吧？
This is a very old problem, okay?
所以我们解决这个问题的方法，基本上是采用了
So the way we solve this problem is basically we employ the old idea of
操作系统中的虚拟内存和分页的老思路。
virtual memory and paging in opening systems.
正如我们都知道的，
So as we all know,
操作系统基本上使用分页来减少物理内存空间的碎片化，对吧？
OS use basically pages to um to reduce fragmentation in the physical memory space, right?
并且使用虚拟内存来高效地实现不同进程之间的空间复用。
So, and use virtual memory for efficient space multiplexing for different processes.
那么在这里，我们所做的基本上是，你可以把每个处理操作系统看作是一个请求。
So here, what we do is basically you can think about each processing OS as a request in, Okay.
我采用了类似的思路来解决
I use similar kind of idea to reserve the fragmentation in
KBCche中的碎片化问题，并实现请求之间的高效空间共享。
KBCche and the unable efficient space sharing between requests.
这也是为什么这个注意力机制被称为分页注意力的原因。
And this is why the other attention is called page attention.
好的，酷。让我们看看吧。
Okay. Cool. Let's see.
我们尽快运行这个，好吗？
Let's run this pretty quickly, okay?
首先，我们要为我的内存分解图中那个粉色部分的GPU内存进行分区，
So to begin with, we first partition the GPU memory for that pink body in my memory breakdown graph,
分成，嗯，分成一个个的token块数组。
into, um, into an array of token blocks.
这里，token块基本上就是一个固定大小的内存块，
So here, a token block is basically a fixed size of chunk of memory that can
可以从左到右存储状态。
store the states from left to right.
这里我持有很多很多块，对吧？
Here I hold many many blocks, right?
我的块数量等于四。
My blocks are equal to four.
好的，为了澄清一下，这里的token不是字符串。
Okay. So to clarify a little bit, so the tokens here are not strings.
它基本上是KB案例对应的token。
It's basically the KB case corresponding tokens.
所以基本上每个token块都会存储每个token的键向量。
So basically each token block will store the key vectors for each token.
好的，所以实际上这不仅仅是一个字节或者类似的东西，而是一个固定大小。
Okay. So it's actually more than just one bites or whatever. It's a fixed size.
这些是token状态，也就是序列中token的向量表示。
So these are token states the vector repetition of the token in sequence.
比如说，在Lama 13 bin模型中，每个token状态会占用大约1兆字节的内存。
So for example, in Lama 13 bin model, each token state would consume about 1 megabyte memory.
这意味着每个token块就是1兆字节，对吧？
Which means that each token block is one megabytte, okay?
是的，所以在此基础上，我们引入了页面注意力机制。
Yeah. So, so on top of this, we basically introduce page attention.
这是注意力核的新实现方式。
So this is a new implementation of the attention kernel.
我们完全改变了执行注意力时的方式，
So we completely change the way like when you perform attention,
也就是你如何从GPU内存中获取内存数据。
how you fetch memories from GPU memory.
之前，你只是从一段连续的内存块中获取数据。
Okay. Previously, you just fetch it from a continuous trunkil memory right on
TBM，但现在我们把它做成了分页的。
TBM but now we make it pages.
所以你必须重新做那个内核初始化。
So you have to redo that kernel inpation.
明白了吗？所以基本上，我们发现了之前系统的根本限制，
Okay? So basically, we find out the fundamental limitation of the previous system that they
他们要求所有QB状态都必须存储在GPU的连续块状内存中。
require all QB states right for a sequence to be stored in a continuous trunkil memory in GPU.
这其实是沿用了典型深度学习工作负载中的一种惯例，
And this is a convention over like in typical deep learning workloads
也就是输入和输出的形状是静态的。
where the input and output ships are static.
我认为很多深度学习框架，比如entropy和priority，都默认采用了这种方式。
I think this was taken by granted by many deep learning frameworks like entropy and priority, okay?
但事实证明，这种方式在推理时非常低效，
But it turns out that uh this is highly inefficient for inference where,
因为序列长度是高度动态的，你无法预知要生成多少个token。
the sequence length are highly dynamic and you don't know how many token you are going to generate.
所以分页注意力机制就是直接针对这个限制提出的。
So basically page attention directly address this limitation.
所以在页面注意力机制中，基本上 QV 缓存是存储在非连续的块状内存中的
So with page attention, basically, the QV catch are basically stored
它们可以被存储在 GPU 内存中的任意位置
in non continuous trunkle memory, and they can be stored in arbitrary position in the GP memory,
但我们有一种机制可以通过页面来管理它们
but we have a mechanism to many them using pages.
所以我们基本上把这个 QV 缓存虚拟化成逻辑和物理的块
So we basically virtualize this QV catch, uh to logical and physical talking blocks.
好的，那我们来看一个例子，看看它是怎么工作的
Okay? So let's see how it works with the example.
这里我有一个请求，提示是“艾伦·图灵是一位计算机科学家”，对吧？
Here I have a request with the prompt Alan Turing is a computer scientist, okay?
所以在逻辑视图中，token 还是被连续地存储在块中
So basically in the logical view, okay, the tokens are still stored in consecutive blocks,
并且 token 的顺序从第一个到最后一个都被保留了
um, and the order is preserved from the first token to the last token.
但我会引入一个页表，这个页表在中间，就是我现在画的这个
But I'm going to introduce a page table where the page table is in the middle, which I who here.
它会把虚拟表映射到实际的物理表，也就是 GPU 内存中的表
And it's going to map the virtual table into the actual physical table, in the GPO memory.
所以基本上在物理视图中，嗯，另一方面，同一序列中的token，
So basically in the physical view, um, on the other hand, the tokens in the same sequence,
它们可能不会被存储在相邻的块中，而且这些块之间的顺序，
they may not be stored in uh adjain blocks, and the order, the orders
是任意的。
between different blocks are arbitrary.
但是我们在这里引入了映射。
But we introduce the mapping here.
基本上，这个映射会告诉你每个逻辑视图
Basically, this mapping is going to tell you how each other logical view
是如何映射到物理视图的。
is going to map to the physical view.
这和操作系统中的页是完全一样的，明白吗？
It's exactly the same as pages in operating systems, okay?
那我们继续这个例子，对吧？
So let's continue with the example, right?
那我们来看一下模型通常预测下一个token的情况。
So let's see the model has generally the next token end.
我们会在逻辑视图中把它写成下一个token是连续的。
And we are going to write this in a logical view as the next token continuously.
但实际发生的是，我们使用块表来查询
But what happened is using the block table, we are going to query where exactly
我们到底应该在物理内存的哪个位置写入数据。
should we write in the physical memory.
在这个表中，它告诉我们应该把u写在
In this table, it tells that we should write u at
物理块编号1的第三个位置。
the physical block number one at the third position.
我们进行索引，找到物理块1的第三个位置，
We do that indexing and we find a physical block one third position,
然后我们就把实际的QB catch写进去。
and we basically write the actual QB catch.
好的。接着我们生成下一个数学家，然后继续
Okay. So then we generate the next to mathematician and we keep
查询这个表，并在对应的位置写入，对吧？
querying the table, and we're right there, right?
你可以看到实际写入并不是连续的。
You can see the actual writing is not continuous.
最后，我们又生成了一个令牌，发现第二个块已经用完了。
And finally, we generate another token and we find the second block is used up.
那我们该怎么办，我们要让内存分配器再给我们一行，对吧？
So what do we do, we are going to ask the memory allocator to give us one more low, right?
这就是我为什么要强调这一点。
So here why I emphasize this.
因为我只是让我的分配器只给我一个。
Because I'm only asking my allocator to give me one
只有在我之前的块用完的时候才再要一个。
more only when my previous talking block was used up.
这样就完全消除了预留的问题。
And this completely remove reservation.
我再也不需要预留了。
I never need to reserve anymore.
为什么预留很糟糕。
Why reservation is pretty bad.
你会承受很大的机会成本。
You suffer a strong opportunity cost.
如果你预留了内存，那些内存就不能被所有集合中的新请求使用。
If you reserve memory, you are not going to make that memory
这样就无法让内存对所有即将到来的请求都可用。
usable for the incoming requests in all set.
这和操作系统中的页表完全一样。
That's exactly the same with page tables in operating systems.
你基本上消除了机会成本。
You basically eliminate the opportunity cost.
好的。那么这里，我发现我的第二个块表已经完成了。
Okay. So here, I found my second block table is done.
我移动到了我的第三行，这一行只在运行时需要时才分配。
I moved to my third third row and this third row was allocated in runtime only when needed.
我一直这样做，按需分配，并继续写入下一个o。好的。
I keep doing this, allocate it on demand and keep writing to next o. Okay.
当有多个请求进入队列时，这种方式效果更好，对吧？
And this is even better when we have multiple requests coming to the queue, right?
因为如果有多个请求，我们基本上会给它们不同的逻辑视图，
Because if you have multiple requests we basically, give them different logical views,
而这些逻辑视图其实都映射到同一个物理空间，
and this logical view we all basically mapped into the same physical space,
这个空间是由内核分页的，对吧？
which is paged, okay, by kernels.
好的，酷。那么总结一下，让我们分析一下页注意力的内存效率。
Okay. Cool. To summarize, okay, uh, let's analyze the memory efficiency of page attention.
所以首先，我们的内部碎片非常少。
So first, we have very minimal internal fragmentation.
为什么？这是因为内部碎片只会出现在序列的最后一个块。
Why? This is because the internal fragmentation only happens at the last block of the sequence.
所以我们的内部碎片被块的大小所限制。
So our internal fragmentation is bonded by the block size.
它不会超过我之前例子中的四个标记。
It's not going to be greater than in my previous example, four tokens.
最多我们只会浪费三个标记。
At most we only wait three tokens.
这基本上消除了内部碎片的问题。
That basically eliminated the internal fragmentation.
我们也没有外部碎片。
We also don't have external fragmentation.
为什么？因为现在我们总是分配固定大小的块，也就是四个标记，
Why? Because now we always allocate a block of fixed size that is four tokens,
所以没有外部碎片。
so there's no external fragmentation.
最后，我们没有预留空间，因为每个块都是按需分配的。
Finally, we don't have reservation because each block is allocated on demand.
所以每当我们需要的时候，我们才分配内存，我们并没有预留任何东西。
So whenever we need it, we allocate we're not reserving anything.
我们完全消除了机会成本。
We completely eliminate the opportunity cost.
基本上因此，你可以在VOM中看到内存利用率大大提高。没错。
Basically as a result, you can see in VOM the memory utilition is greatly improved. Agree.
是的。我们基本上消除了外部和重分配的成本。
Yeah. We basically eliminate the external and retribon cost.
好的。我们得到了96.3%的利用率，你的补充也没问题。
Okay. And we get a 96.3% okay your addition.
好的，那这基本上就结束了。
Okay, so that'll basically wrap up.
请大家注意一下。有问题吗？可以提问。
Put your attention. Any question? Yeah.
嗯，我们需要……对。
Um, we need. Yeah.
好的。我这里有一些传闻。
Okay. I have some rumors here.
基本上当我们构建这个V的时候，我觉得Jensen非常生气。
Basically when we build this V I think Jensen is pretty mad.
嗯，他的意思是，你应该是构建这个B媒体的人，B媒体应该更加
Um he sort of like, you should be media who builds this B media should be more
熟悉他们的硬件，并且应该以分页的方式来管理他们的GPU内存。
familiar with their hardware and this should manage their GPU memory in a way that is page.
但事实证明，是我们先做到了这一点。
But it turns out that we build this first.
是的。这也是为什么我们现在和媒体公司密切合作，并且我们试图将这个功能
Yeah. That's why we now collaborating with media pretty closely, and we try to push this into
推进到他们的GPU中，作为一个原生特性。
their GPU as a native feature.
嗯，好的，好的，很酷。
Yeah. Okay. Okay, cool.
我想我已经介绍了第二个关键技术，分页注意力，显然这个分页注意力
I think I covered the second key technique, page attention, and apparently this page attention
已经开始流行起来了。请继续。
has already taken off. Yeah, please.
嗯，我不太确定，但我觉得当我们在2023年发布这个的时候，我们在推理服务上领先于open。
Yeah. I don't know, but I think when we part this in 2023, we are ahead of open on serving.
是的，所以基本上，当我们发布这个的时候，
Yeah. So basically, when we put this,
我认为这会带来巨大的影响
I think this make a huge impact to
Google Dibne 和 Open Air，他们都在尝试模仿我们的技术。
Google Dibne and open air, they all try to mimic our technique.
是的。好的。是个很好的问题。
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Very good question.
你做应用时，是的。你运行16的块大小，
You do application. Yeah. You run block size of 16,
32、64，然后找出最优的那个，调优内核。
32, 64 and you figure out the one that is best, you tune the kernels.
是的，是的。这基本上取决于块的大小。
Yeah. Yeah. It depends on basically block size.
我觉得我是在提问的时候想到的。
I think I create with asking the question.
如果你的块大小很小，那么你的索引成本会更高。
If you have very small block size, then your indexing cost is higher.
如果你的块很大，基本上就回到了
If you have a large piece you basically go back to
连续内存的模式。所以你需要进行调优。
the continuous memory regime. So you have to tune it.
嗯，好吧。我觉得这基本上是很多人2023年最喜欢的论文。
Yeah. Okay. And this is basically I think this is many people's favorite paper in 2023.
因为这将推理的成本提升了三倍。是的，非常不错。
Because this improves the inference soaring cost by three X. Yeah, pretty good.
好的，希望你喜欢这一部分，好吗？
Okay. I hope you enjoy this part, okay?
那我们接下来来看一个更新的技术。
And then let's move on to an even newer technique.
我想我已经尝试回答了你的问题。
And I think I try to answer your question.
很明显那个学生已经帮忙回答了这个问题，对吧？
So apparently that student already aided the question, right?
所以当你进行连续批处理时，确实提升了加法的效率，因为你
So when you do continuous batching, you indeed improve the addition because you
批处理时，在运行MLP时会做一个很大的批次。
batch you make a pretty batch when you run MLP per.
但问题是，比如说前缀非常长，对吧？
But the problem is, say a prefew is super long, right?
所以解码时每个请求只有一个token。
So a decode only have one token per request.
本质上，如果你把它们全部放在一起，你其实是在说只做
Essentially, if you put all them together, you are saying only doing
你最大化吞吐量的事情，是的，但你会延迟其他解码请求的延迟。
what you maximize your throughput, yes, but you are delaying the latency
那么我们该如何解决这个问题呢？
for other decoding requests.
让我们看看吧。这是一个非常热门的话题
So how do fix that problem?
我必须要讲，因为我认为今年，
Let's see. This is a pretty hot topic
2025年，很多公司都在从C speci架构转向这种架构。
I have to cover because I think this year,
它被称为预字段解码解耦，我说，这有什么问题吗？
2025, a lot of company they are moving into this architecture from C speci.
好的。所以我觉得，正如我已经多次强调的那样，好吗？
It's called pre field decode desegregation and I say, what's the problem?
至少在2023年和2024年，人们基本上都在追求所谓的吞吐量指标。
Okay. So I think, as I have already ind many times, okay?
So at least in 2023 and 24, people are basically trying to grind this so called throughput metric.
他们试图在有限的资源下，最大化每秒可以处理的token数量。
They try to maximize the number of tokens they can serve per second given a limited lumbaus you
你可以看到这个上限一直在被突破，比如24倍、3.5倍之类的。
can see this limit keep being pushed higher, uh, like 24 X,
3.5倍或者其他数值。
3.5 X or whatever.
L基本上就是决定了这个吞吐量。
L basically ground this throughput.
明白了吗？但除了吞吐量之外，好吗？
Okay? But besides throughput, okay?
许多应用是作为服务提供给用户的。
Many applications, they are offered as a service to users.
因此，对于这些服务来说，我们还有一些同样重要的指标，
Therefore, for such services, we do have some equally important metrics,
我们称之为服务级别目标，简称SLO。
which we call service level objectives, or in short, SO.
你可能在很多地方、很多公司都听说过这个词，
You've probably heard about this work many many places many companies,
他们都想保证所谓的SLO。
they want to guarantee so called SO.
好吗？在ARM中，有两个最重要的服务级别目标。
Okay? So in ARM there are uh two most important service level objectives.
一个叫做TTFT，另一个叫做TPOT。
One is called TTFToh the other is called TPOT.
这两个词听起来有点奇怪，但我们试着记住它们。
This is a pretty weird, word, but let's try to remember them.
所以TTFT是指第一个……
So TTFTT to first too.
TPOT是每个输出标记的时间。那么它们是什么意思呢？
TVOT time per output token. So what do they mean?
好的。像HGBT这样的聊天机器人，需要有相对较快的初始响应。
Okay. So a chat bot, like HGBT, they need to have a relatively fast initial response.
因此，TDOT越低越好。
Therefore, lower TDOT.
也就是说，当你在HTP中输入内容时，你希望尽快看到第一个词。
That is when you type a car into HTP, you expect to see the first word as soon as possible.
你不想等待，否则体验会很差，对吧？
You don't want to wait. Otherwise, it's a pretty bad experience, right?
但是当第一个标记被生成出来时，如果你……
But when the first token was generated, if you ever I'm
你应该用过CHITP吧，对吧？
pretty sure you have ever used the CHITP right?
你可以看到ChatB的token是一个接一个地被流式输出的。
You can see the ChatB token was streamed, one by one.
所以一旦你看到第一个token，你就会从第一个token开始阅读。
So once you observe the first token, you are going to read from the first token.
从服务提供者的角度来看，这就是一个问题。
And from a service provider's perspective, what a problem.
只要他们生成token的速度和你的阅读速度一样快，那就没问题。
So as long as they can generate tokens as fast as your reading speed, they are good.
因为你不可能比生成的速度读得更快，对吧？
Because you are not going to read faster than what the generated, okay?
所以，基本上，为了让用户体验更好，他们需要更低的DFT。
So um so basically, um, in order to make the user experience better, they need to have a lower DFT.
但在那之后，后续生成的文本就不需要
But after that, okay, the following generated text doesn't have to
比人类的平均阅读速度更快了。
be faster than the average reading speed over human.
那你每分钟能读多少个单词？
So how many words you can read per minute?
我可以告诉你数字。
I can tell you number.
大约是15550个英文单词。是的。
It's roughly 15550 words in English. Yeah.
好的。所以你不知道怎么比这个更快，但你不能比这个更慢。
Okay. So you don't know how to be faster than that, but you cannot be slower than that.
否则，你就不需要等待了。
Otherwise, you don't have to wait.
好的。这意味着TPOT，也就是每个输出token的时间，
Okay. So this means that the TPOT that is the time per output token
在生成第一个token之后，其实不需要很快，
after the initial token generated, doesn't have to be fast,
才能满足用户体验。
in order to make satisfy the user experience.
好的。但相反，比如说，我们有另一个任务M任务，就是摘要，对吧？
Okay. But in contrast, okay, say, we have another task M task, which is summarization, right?
所以用户会用一个摘要应用，他们其实可以接受
So der will use a summarizing application, and they can actually tolerate
更长的初始响应时间，因为当你试图向RM提交一批文档时，
a longer initial response because when you try to submit a batch of documents to RM,
you don't want to see the first token immediately, you want to see
the eventual results as early as possible.
So in that case, you don't have to prioritize your time to first token because the user doesn't
care about that. They just want to see.
S, after 1 hour I eventually see, uh, my summarizations, right.
So in this case,
TTF T is not important, but TPOT is important because we want to generate as far as possi.
Okay. And this gives you a sense of what is TDFD and TOT, okay?
So then the question is, in the presence of these two SOs,
TDFT and TBOTuh is throughput sufficiently good measure for arm serving systems?
事实证明，情况并不总是如此。
And turns out that this is not always the case.
假设我们有一个系统，每秒可以处理十个请求。
So, suggest that we have a system that can serve ten requests per second.
这是我们的系统容量，对吧？
That's our system capacity, okay?
但是当我们对TDFE和TPOT施加实际约束时，也就是说我们需要解决t个请求，
But when we post actual constraint on TDFE and TPOT, okay, that is we need to solve t requests,
并且还需要满足服务级别目标。
and we also need to satisfy the service level objective.
也就是说，TTFT需要保持在200毫秒以内，TPOT需要保持在50毫秒以内。
That is, TTFT need to stay within 200 milliseconds, and TPOT need to stay within 50 minutes seconds.
好，我们加上这两个约束。
Okay, we put these two constraints.
如果我加上这两个约束，你会发现，很多请求
And if I put this two constraints, you can see, many requests
并没有满足这个约束，对吧？
are not satisfying request this constraint, right?
也就是说，它们实际上并没有达到服务质量要求。
Meaning that they are not actually meeting the service level quality, okay?
所以我们把这部分受限于约束的吞吐量称为有效吞吐量。
So we call the portion of this throughput that is subject to the constraint as as goodput.
也就是说，这是吞吐量中“有效”的那一部分。
So that is the good part of this throughput.
这就是为什么它被称为有效吞吐量。
That's why it's called goodput.
明白了吗？所以你可以看到，“有效吞吐量”这个词其实会让你想起一些很早以前学过的东西，
Okay? So you can see, um, the term goodput properly, reminds you of some very old things
可能是你在学计算机网络时学到的。
that you learned from, uh, maybe computer networks.
我觉得在快递包裹时，他们也会对这些东西加以限制，对吧？
I think when they do package delivery, they also put a constraint on these kind of things, right?
所以在这里，你可以看到。
So here, you can see.
嗯，对不起，其实我还想补充一些类似的想法。
Um, I'm sorry indeed share some more similar idea.
这基本上意味着高吞吐量并不总是能转化为高有效吞吐量，
So this basically means that high throughput cannot always translate into high goodput once we
一旦我们把延迟因素考虑进来，就是这样。
factor the latency into this picture, okay?
嗯，好吧。这引出了我们要问的另一个重要问题。
Um, Okay. So this leads us to ask another important question.
那么，为什么现有系统无法实现这种高吞吐量呢？
So why do existing systems they fail to achieve this kind of high goodput.
好吗？让我们退一步，来了解一下一个请求是如何通过RM的。
Okay? And let's take a step back and understand how a request goes through the RM.
在这里，我为你画了一个很漂亮的G，好吗？
And here I make a pretty nice G for you, okay?
我会让你看10秒钟，好吗。
So I will let you look at it for 10 seconds. Okay.
基本上，我想我在图中想表达的是我在条件批处理中介绍的内容，
So basically, I think what I try to convey in chief is what I introduced in condition batching,
你的预取和解码，它们是一起批处理的。
uh your prefuel and decoding, they are batched together.
好的，我想你已经读到了那个问题。
Okay. And I think you already read that question.
所以如果预取非常繁重，那么你的解码就会被延迟
So if the prefel is pretty heavy, then your decoding is going to be delayed
因为高速公路上的预取工作负载。
because of the highway work load prefuel.
好吗？这就是条件批处理的一个主要缺点。
Okay? That is one major drawback for conditions batching.
好吗？所以，嗯，让我再重申一下，基本上预填充是非常依赖计算的，
Okay? So, um, so let me reiterate basically prefuel is very compute bond,
意思是说，一个小批量的预填充，当你计算预填充阶段时，
meaning that a small batch of prefill they are like when you compute the prefiel face,
它们就像你在做训练一样。
they are like you are doing training.
这非常消耗计算资源，即使是一个小批量的预填充，也能让GPU的计算资源饱和。
It's pretty computer heavy, and a small batch of pre fuel, they can saturate the GPU competition.
但另一方面，解码，对吧，他们需要
But on the other hand, the decode, right, they need
更大的批量，因为S等于1，对吧。
a much bigger size because S equal to one, right.
所以他们需要更大的批量才能真正饱和计算资源，这意味着他们有
So they need a much bigger size to actually sat with the competition, which means that they have
非常不同的计算特性。
very distinct computational characteristics.
而且，因为连续批处理基本上会优先考虑解码。
And, um, and because continuous batching basically cool case prefer decode,
在同一个批次中，这两个阶段实际上会相互干扰。
right into the same batch, the two phases actually interfere with each other.
好的，那我们来看一下对比。
Okay. So let's see a comparison here.
在左边，呃，我们批处理RON R二，你可以看到第一个是RN，第二个是R二，RA
So on the left, um, uh, we batch RON R two, o you can see the first is RN second R two and RA
正在经历解码阶段，
is going through the decoding phase and
R R二正在经历预填充阶段，我们将把这两个批次合并在一起。
R R two is going through the prefill phase, and we are going to put these two batches together.
好的，我们可以看到在红色窗口和粉色窗口中，
Okay. So we can see that in the red window in the pink window,
当Art到达时，RO的解码时间是在蓝色区域。
when Art arrives, ROs decode time, which is in blue.
一旦你用并行批处理把它们放到同一个批次里，
It will once you put it into the same batch using con batching,
它会被明显延迟，对吧？
it will be significantly delayed, right?
因为Rtools的预填充会花更长时间。
Because Rtools prefer will take longer. Okay.
And same thing, actually arts prefel also get a little bit
delayed because you batch the decode into Rtools perfil.
Okay. But if I do this, suppose I have a way.
Basically I run RN RT to prevent decoding on different dips. I don't have this problem.
So RN decode will continue following its own pace, and RT will just do its profile.
Okay? And I can make this even more serious.
In reality, what happens is, you have a streaming of requests coming. Okay.
Every time you pick up new requests, put into the continued batching,
you are going to introduce a pre fuel that is going to interfere with the decode or other requests.
And this can create a cascade of interference.
所以基本上，如果你继续批处理，是的，效用会很高，但这个解码，
So basically, if you continue to continue batching, yes, utility is high, but this decode,
它们就会被延迟。
they are going to be delayed.
如果你对解码有延迟限制，你就无法满足收听延迟。
And if you have a latency constraint on decode, you are not going to meet listening delay.
好的，收听限制。
Okay, listening constraint.
抱歉。好的。那么如果你想要像GBT那样提供优质服务，
Sorry. Okay. So then if you want to basically to a good service like GBT,
你想在满足收听限制的同时最大化吞吐量，你该怎么做。
you want to maximize your sput while you still meet the listening constraint what you do.
好的。由于这种干扰，当服务必须同时满足TDF和TPOT时，
Okay. As a result of this interference, uh, when service must satisfy both TDF and TPOT,
他们的做法基本上是增加倍数。
um, what they do is they basically add multiples.
是的，他们分配多个倍数来减少干扰。
Yeah, they allocate multiples to basically diminish the interference.
好的。显然，增加倍数的问题在于你要付出代价。
Okay. Um apparently, the reason the problem of adding multiple is that you're going to pay
更多的是为了满足你的服务质量，对吧？
more to satisfy your service quality, right?
好吗？那解决方案是什么？
Okay? So what's the solution?
解决方案其实很简单。
The solution is pretty simple.
我觉得你已经明白了。
I think you already get that.
我们为什么不把预览和解码放在不同的GPU上呢？
Why don't we just put preview and decod on different dips.
我们不再进行批处理了。
We're not going to batch anymore.
我们基本上就是把预览和解码放在不同的GPU上，这其实就是一个例子，
We just basically put prefer and deco on different dipUsT if basically gives you an example where,
嗯，我分配了两块GPU。
um, I allocate two GPUs.
第一块GPU基本上处理所有的预览任务。
The first GPU basically take all the preview job.
一旦它完成了预览，
And once it finishes prefiw,
我将把第一个DPU的QB捕获转发到第二个DPU。
I'm going to forward the QB catch from the first DPU to second DPU.
然后我会在第二个DPO中批量处理所有解码。
And then I batch all the decode in the second DPO.
这样，我可以完全消除优先解码之间的干扰。
In that way, I can completely eliminate the interference between preferent decode.
这让系统变得更加复杂。
This makes the system even more complicated.
为什么？之前我是在一块GPU上完成所有操作，对吧？
Why? Previously, I do everything on one single GPU, right?
我只是把所有事情都在内核级别完成，现在你让我
I just do everything in a kernel level, and now you're asking me to do
搭建一个分布式系统来进行通信。
a distribute system on how to communicate.
但这就是我们现在正在做的，好吗？
But this is what we do today, okay?
我会在最后一节课揭示为什么这样做会更好。
I'm going to reveal why this can be better in the last lecture.
好的，谢谢大家。
Okay, thank you.